<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ancient and durable gospel. Concerning the time of the perfect and totall subduing, washing away, remitting, blotting out, and pardoning, believers sins : and believers being justified, adopted, married to Christ; and presented by Christ spotlesse. Shewing, that though these things were in purpose before the world was, in prophesie, and promise, before Christ dyed; purchased just then; and applyed by faith when we believe. Yet the said purpose is not executed; the said prophesies are not accomplisht; nor promises fulfilled; the things purchased are not effected, nor by us fully enjoyed, till Christs second comming : at which time the saints that sleep shall arise : and scattered Israel shall be gathered. / Written by Thomas Kilcop. In two books; the one iu [sic] an orderly sermon-method : the other by way of answer to a book intituled. Justification by Christ alone : a good title, were the book but sutable.</title>
            <author>Killcop, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87719</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867653</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119974</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248499741</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1166_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208730</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867653</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867653e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119974)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1166[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ancient and durable gospel. Concerning the time of the perfect and totall subduing, washing away, remitting, blotting out, and pardoning, believers sins : and believers being justified, adopted, married to Christ; and presented by Christ spotlesse. Shewing, that though these things were in purpose before the world was, in prophesie, and promise, before Christ dyed; purchased just then; and applyed by faith when we believe. Yet the said purpose is not executed; the said prophesies are not accomplisht; nor promises fulfilled; the things purchased are not effected, nor by us fully enjoyed, till Christs second comming : at which time the saints that sleep shall arise : and scattered Israel shall be gathered. / Written by Thomas Kilcop. In two books; the one iu [sic] an orderly sermon-method : the other by way of answer to a book intituled. Justification by Christ alone : a good title, were the book but sutable.</title>
                  <author>Killcop, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.H. and are to be sold by Giles Calvert, living at the sign of the Black-spread Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the year 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Marsh. 31.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Justification by Christ alone.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:1"/>
                  <p>ANCIENT AND DURABLE GOSPEL. Concerning the time of the PERFECT and totall subduing, washing away, remitting, blotting out, and pardoning, Believers sins: And Believers being Justified, adopted, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Christ; and presented by Christ spotlesse.</p>
                  <p>Shewing, that though these things were in purpose before the world was, in Prophesie, and promise, before Christ dyed; purchased just then; and applyed by faith when we believe. Yet the said purpose is not executed; the said prophesies are not accomplisht; nor promises ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled; the things purchased are not effected, nor by us fully enjoyed, till Christs second comming: at which time the Saints that sleep shall arise: and scattered Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el shall be gathered.</p>
                  <p>Written by <hi>THOMAS KILCOP.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In two Books; the one in an orderly Sermon-method: the other by way of answer to a Book intituled, <hi>Justification by Christ alone:</hi> A good Title, were the Book but sutable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. H.</hi> And are to be sold by <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> living at the sign of the Black-spread <hi>Eagle</hi> at the west end of <hi>Pauls. In the Year</hi> 1648.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:2"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian reader keep</hi> to the Law and Testimony, he that walketh not by this word, hath not light in him, <hi>Isa.</hi> 8, 20. Turne not to either hand, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4, 27. <hi>There is in people a lyablenesse to erre one way in shunning errour another; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Some preach preparations for Christ; and say wee must be so and so qualified before we may believe: others erre on the other band in shunning this; and tell us, that the Elect are in Christ; are Justified; Adopted, &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they believe; and that all their sinnes past, present, and to come, are pardoned; yea, before they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Against the first, Scripture saith,</hi> The spirit and Bride say, come, let him that thirsteth come: let whoever will take of the water of life freely; come, without money or price, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>'Tis not the number of greatnesse of sinne, nor the want of qualifications, nor any consideration in the World, will cause Christ to reject any commer: but who ever thou art, or whatever thy condition be, come and
<pb facs="tcp:119974:3"/>welcome, for whoever comes to him,</hi> hee will in no wise cast off, Joh. 6.37.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But though Christ is alwaies ready to receive every commer; and though every commer shall have through him, Justification, Adoption, Remission, Eternal Life, &amp;c. yet they that come not, share not herein,</hi> Such as believe he Justifieth from all things, Acts 13. whoever believeth shal receive remission of sins, Acts 10.43. He that hath the Son hath life, but he that hath not him hath not life, 1 Joh. 5, 10.11. He gives power to be Sons of God to them that receive him, even the believers on his name, Joh. 1.12. <hi>So that to conclude, Christ is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for all commers, come who will, receive him; and have all: but reject him; and want all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Again, the Papists erre one way, taking metaphors literally, and many seeing their errour, erre as bad on the other side, in turning proper speeches to a spiritual sence: but good it is, to know the direct mind of God in every Scripture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is good to understand Comparisons, Comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Doctrines, Doctrinally; and Parables, Parabollically: to understand Histories, Historically; and Prophesies, Prophetically: to understand Metaphors, Metaphorically; and Proper Speeches, Properly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord teach us to discerne between Histories, and Prophesies: between Metaphors, and Proper Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and to know when Christ in his word speakes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, and when he speakes plainly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:3"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And so to doe, it is good, first, to reject nothing at a venter,</hi> Condemne not before thou hear, Joh. 7.51. Speake not evill of what thou knowest not, Jud. 10. <hi>and thus to doe, first reject nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause such and such rare Christians doe: follow them, but as they follow Christ. Secondly, reject no message for the meannesse of the messenger,</hi> for God hides from the wise and learned, what he reveales to Babes Mat. 11.25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also, take not all that is taught for currant Doctrin, but try whether it be of God,</hi> try all things, hold fast what is good, 1 Thess. 5, 21. <hi>and herein first, feare not the tryall of what thou hast been trained up in.</hi> Acts 22.3. <hi>Secondly, credit no mans bare word, but try it by Scripture,</hi> Act. 17, 11. <hi>and herein try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quotations be to purpose or not, and whether they alter not the sence, and whether they mistake not the scope of the place, and be earnest with God to give thee discerning,</hi> If thou callest for knowledge, and cryest for understanding: if thou seekest her as silver, and searchest for her as for treasure: then thou shalt understand the feare of the Lord, Prov. 2.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>So farewell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in Christs Cause,<lb/>
                        <hi>Tho. Kilcop</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="summary_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:4"/>
                  <div n="1" type="book">
                     <head>The contents of the first Booke.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                        <p>Touching the scope of the Text, the dividing and opening of the words: &amp; the difference betweene purging and washing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Doct.</hi> Man un-cleansed, is throughout filthy.</p>
                        <p>8 particulars herein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                        <p n="1">I. Man un-cleansed is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
                        <p n="2">II. He is so throughout.</p>
                        <p n="3">III. Every one is so.</p>
                        <p n="4">IV. How they became so.</p>
                        <p n="5">V. When they became so.</p>
                        <p n="6">VI. How long they abide so.</p>
                        <p n="7">VII. what befalleth them in their so being. As,</p>
                        <p n="1">1. A separation from God.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Loss of all good.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Possession of all evill.</p>
                        <p n="8">VIII. What we may learn from this Doctrine.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. To suffer patiently.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To be humble.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To observe the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing richness of Gods love, virtue of Christs death; need of his interceding.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Doct.</hi> God cleanseth man from his filth compleatly.</p>
                        <p>Herein nine things is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Man cannot compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleanse himselfe.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. God cleanseth man compleatly: for he clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, 1. The whole man.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. from all sin.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. For ever.</p>
                        <p n="3">III. Who God cleanseth.</p>
                        <p n="4">IV. What compleat clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing is: namely, the strip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sin off its being; yea, it hath in it six things.</p>
                        <p>To wit, the subduing, washing away, removing, destroying, loosing and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting of sin.</p>
                        <p n="5">V. When God cleanseth.</p>
                        <p n="6">VI. Wherewith God cleanseth.</p>
                        <p n="7">VII. What accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies compleat cleansing. To wit, 1. Pardon. 2. Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. 3. Perfect enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. Consisting of the perfit knowledge of God; the perfect union with God, and perfect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety
<pb facs="tcp:119974:4"/>in God.</p>
                        <p n="8">VIII. When God cleanseth people compleatly. which is, 1. After Christ death. 2. After their owne birth. Yea, 3. after they believe. 4. After they dye. Proved with seven particulars.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Just at Christ second comming, <hi>when the dead in Christ shall rise, and the Jewes shall be gathered;</hi> and good reason that should be the time.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Because Christ is not a preventer, but a redeemer.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Because the earthly must be borne before the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Because Christ weding day is just then.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Because the new Covenant is then, and not till then accomplisht.</p>
                        <p n="9">IX. What this doctrine may teach us; it informes us, 1. of the difference between expective, and active en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments. 2. of the concurrence of many Schriptures, which else would jarre. Lastly, it teacheth believers pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="book">
                     <head>The contenths of the <hi>2.</hi> Booke.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                        <p>Justification in Christ, and in our consciences in differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent respects. Not only Christ death, but also his resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ascention, and second comming, tendeth to our happines. We are justified by faith, yet faith doth not justifie. Justified by Christ, also by faith, but in different respects, we have by faith, what faith moves not God to give. Ungodly before; but not after Justification. Faith is not Christs partner, yet what Christ hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chast, Faith applieth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="chapter">
                        <pb facs="tcp:119974:5"/>
                        <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5. Is the speech of believers spoken in faith. The difference between both parties is stated.</p>
                        <p n="4">IV. Things proved. 1. We were not spotless. 2. nor presented so when Christ dyed.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We shall be faultless. 4. And so presented, when Christ appeares.</p>
                        <p>Five queries as healps to understand <hi>Daniels</hi> seventy weekes.</p>
                        <p>While things are to doe, they are not finished.</p>
                        <p>Bloud is shed before it is sprinckled, and sprinckled before it elenseth: sin remains not when it is washt away; and needeth no destruction when it is utterly destroyed.</p>
                        <p>There is no defilement after perfect cleansing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                        <p>Christ is made sinne, and cursed for us first: wee are righteous and blest in him afterwards.</p>
                        <p>We are not blest, til after we believe; nor healed, till after converted. Justification and healing at Christs next ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing.</p>
                        <p>The time of purchase is past: and time of redemption to come, but all ready promised, and by faith enjoyed.</p>
                        <p>Though sin be not destroyed, it shall be, for Christs worke shall prosper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                        <p>Tipes are in Gospel times usefull.</p>
                        <p>As we sin'd not in <hi>Adam,</hi> before we were in <hi>Adam:</hi> we are not righteous in Christ, before we are in Christ.</p>
                        <p>We are not righteous in the second <hi>Adam,</hi> till after we fin in the first: atonements were made to cleanse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they did cleanse.</p>
                        <p>The scape <hi>Goat</hi> carried sin away, after the slain <hi>Goat</hi> was slain. Perfection by Christ, is after comming to Christ.</p>
                        <p>Perfection is not while interceding lasteth.</p>
                        <p>Christ is (as yet) in expectation.</p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119974:5"/>
                        <p> Christ by dying is an author, not a finisher.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                        <p>We need no more offering to purchase: but the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of what this hath purchased is needfull.</p>
                        <p>Christs first comming was to purchase, and not to effect.</p>
                        <p>Christ bloud must be applyed, before it justifieth.</p>
                        <p>Prophesies speak of things to come, as being present.</p>
                        <p>Christ whole Spouse is spotlesse; but some without others are not.</p>
                        <p>We shall be as sin-less when Christ appeares, as he is now: which thing faith applyeth.</p>
                        <p>Christ bearing iniquity is the cause, Justification the effect.</p>
                        <p>We are not cleansed from all sins while any spect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, (to present) is not (hath presented.</p>
                        <p>Some thing is finished, but Iustification is not.</p>
                        <p>Our Iustification is amongst others) one end of Christs resurrection.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                        <p>Sufficiencie to effect, is before effecting.</p>
                        <p>Christ at his first comming, merritted glory for us. And shall at his next comming confer it one us.</p>
                        <p>Christs passive obedience is ours, but not his active.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Isay.</hi> 53.3, 4, 5, 6. with other such places, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesies, not histories.</p>
                        <p>Gods forbearance is till Christs next comming, and then sins shall to believers be remitted.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                        <p>Sin is remitted after it is committed.</p>
                        <p>Pardon is purchased, before effected, the one is past, and the other to come. Pardon ought to be praid for, for many reasons, when we are not only called but justified and glorified, then nothing shall be laid to our charge. God gives faith first, and justifieth only Believers; but not for believing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="chapter">
                        <pb facs="tcp:119974:6"/>
                        <head>CHAP. VIII</head>
                        <p>Our being in Christ is purposed, before it is prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                        <p>Vessels of mercy, were children of wrath, since Christ dyed.</p>
                        <p>There was both law and curse, before <hi>Moses,</hi> and is since.</p>
                        <p>Believers are to this day under the curse laid on <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>God hates not only works, but also workers of iniquity.</p>
                        <p>First to justify afterwards call, is contrary to Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of grace.</p>
                        <p>Filthy actions, defile the actors.</p>
                        <p>Gods love from eternity was but in purpose.</p>
                        <p>Condemned, is one thing, damned another. All in <hi>Adam</hi> are condemned, but all are not damned.</p>
                        <p>The ridance of sin, is fince Christ dyed; spoken of in the future tence.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
                        <p>That we are not in Christ by faith, and that the visible Church is called Christ, are notable errours.</p>
                        <p>Christ is a Rock and Tower: and we are by faith on him, and in him.</p>
                        <p>It is besid, yea, against Scripture to say he that believes not, or obeyes not, shall be saved.</p>
                        <p>Christ the only meanes, so as to purchase: and faith a meanes, so as to apply,</p>
                        <p>we were from eternity predestinate to be adopted.</p>
                        <p>Adoption is not before believing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. X.</head>
                        <p>Scripture doth not call Christ saith.</p>
                        <p>That saith opposed to workes, and by which we are Instified is not Christ, for it is the faith of Christ, faith in Christ; a faith perfected by workes. That faith that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth promises, which is counted for righteousness, by
<pb facs="tcp:119974:6"/>which we are sons, or by which we live, is beliefe.</p>
                        <p>Scripture expressions will agree, when ours Jarre.</p>
                        <p>Faith saveth applyingly, Baptisme figuratively, and Christ meritoriously, that is attributed to Christ, that is not to faith.</p>
                        <p>We are by faith Justified before God: and our faith by workes before men.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. XI</head>
                        <p>God seeth things as they be: He seeth us filthy while we are so: and spotless when we are spotless.</p>
                        <p>Christ is our righteousness, propitiation, &amp;c. through faith, not otherwise. Righteousness through faith, was held forth in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time.</p>
                        <p>We reckon Christ all in all, in seeking righteousness by the faith of Christ.</p>
                        <p>Faith cannot be set a part from Christ.</p>
                        <p>Actions done without faith, are not reckoned righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions.</p>
                        <p>We are Justified by faith, yet not till after believing.</p>
                        <p>God first cals, and afterward justifieth, and this order faith applieth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
                        <p>Faith is requisite to salvation, yet no conditionall cause thereof.</p>
                        <p>The Covenant of grace was made with man, even with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the house of Israel. Faith is not a fruit of the said Covenant.</p>
                        <p>When the habit of Justice is restored, we shall be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified.</p>
                        <p>We are Justified in purpose, prophesie, promise, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase: but not in accomplishment, performance, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, as yet.</p>
                        <p>God will not cleare the guilty, nor pronounce us just till we are so.</p>
                        <p>Justification is discovered to us, before effected in us.</p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119974:7"/>
                        <p> It is as great a light to see our selves justified, as to see sin taken out of our consciences.</p>
                        <p>That fin should be utterly destroyed and washed away for ever, and a bide in the conscience also, is contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</p>
                        <p>We have faith before all sin is took out of our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:7"/>
                  <head>ANCIENT <hi>and durable</hi> GOSPEL.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Psalme. 51.7.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Purge me with Isop and I shall be clean. wash me, and I shall be whiter then Snow.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE pen-man of this Psalme was <hi>David;</hi> the sight of his sin committed with <hi>Bershebah,</hi> occasioned it; as the Title declares.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David</hi> herein, First, desires God to blot out his fin; <hi>ver.</hi> 1. Secondly, to cleanse him from it. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged thus to petition, from a cousideration of the sight he had of it, and sorrow for it; being by faith per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, that God which gave him a sight of it, and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for it, would also blot it out, and cleanse him of it. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. Fourthly, to the praise of God, he acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his sinne to be against God; and God to be just in judging. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. and by way of aggravation, minds the rice of his sinn, to be from his very conception. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. Lastly. In confidence of Gods mercy. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. uttereth. this petition, <hi>Purge me with Isop and I shall be clean; wash me and I shall be whiter then Snow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119974:8"/>
                  <p> These words are a petition, with an argument of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to be heard. The petition is for purity; and is double, <hi>purge me, wash me, &amp;c. purging</hi> is inward clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>washing,</hi> is outward cleansing. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.2. The word <hi>Isop,</hi> leads us to the bloud of Christ; that as the Priests under the law, dipt <hi>Isop</hi> in the bloud of the Sacrifice, and besprinckled the unclean therewith, to cleanse them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 14 6, 7. so God by giving faith, besprinckles our hearts, with the bloud of Christ, for to cleanse them: <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. with 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. his argument to be heard, is drawne from the compleatnes of the the thing done, if God doe it. This also is doubled. <hi>I shall be clean,</hi> to wit, inwardly, <hi>I shall be whiter then Snow,</hi> to wit outwardly.</p>
                  <p>This Petition argues his acknowledgement.</p>
                  <p>First that he is filthy. And secondly, un-able to cleanse himselfe.</p>
                  <p>His argument declares his confidence touching the willingnes of God to purge the inside, and wash the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side.</p>
                  <p>From hence ariseth these two observations.</p>
                  <p>First, That man uncleansed, is throughout filthy.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, God only doth cleanse man compleatly from this filth. And these two points I shall briefly handle.</p>
                  <p>First, That man un-cleansed, is throughout filthy.</p>
                  <p>And herein I shall declare these eight particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That un-cleansed man is filthy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He is so throughout.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Every one is so.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. How.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. When they became so.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Howlong they abide so.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. What befals them in their so being.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. What we may learn from it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Man before he is cleansed, is silthy. <hi>What is Man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119974:8"/>that be should be clean, or one born of a woman, that beshould be righteous:</hi> he, that is God, <hi>seeth folly in his Angels, yea, the beavens are unclean in his sight: how much more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable and uncleane is man, which drinketh iniquity as water.</hi> Job 15.14, 15, 16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He is filthy throughout, even in body and soule: the body is so, and that from top to toe: <hi>they are gone out of the way, and are altogether abominable: their throat is an open sepulchre, their tongues use deceit; their mouth is full of cursing; their feet are swift to shed bloud.</hi> Rom. 3.14, 15. <hi>From the sole of the foot to the head, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whole, &amp;c.</hi> Esay. 1.6. Also their souls are wholy filthy <hi>every thought of mans heart is only evill, and that continually,</hi> Gen. 6.5. <hi>To the defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure, but even their minds and cansciences are defiled.</hi> Tit. 1.15. yea, his best state is thus; <hi>his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes is but drosse and dunge.</hi> Phil. 4.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Every one before he be cleansed, is thus; even all that come of <hi>Adam. They have corrupted and done abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable wickednesse: there is none that doth good noe not one. The Lord looked down from heaven, to see if any would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, and seek after God. Every one is gone back, they are altogether corrupt; there is none that doth good no not one</hi> Psalme 53.1, 2, 3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They became thus filthy, by reason of sinne, were it nor for sin, man were clean, and not filthy; <hi>that that commeth out of man, defileth him; for from the heart pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth evill thoughts, adulteries, fornication, murder, covetousnesse, wickednesse, deceit, blasphemy, pride, &amp;c. these come from within, and defile the man.</hi> Marke 7.20, 21, 22.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The time when man became thus filthy, is, the time of his first being; he is so even from the wombe. <hi>Man new born, is like the wild Asse Colt.</hi> Job 11.12. <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of a filthy, not one.</hi> Job. 25.4.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119974:9"/>
                     <hi>I was born in Iniquity, and in sin my mother conceived me, Psal.</hi> 51.4.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Man abideth thus filthy, generally, till he be washt Ezek. 16.4. More particularly, they are filthy, yea wholy filthy till they beleive; <hi>for to the unbelieving is nothing pure, but even their mindes and consciences are defiled; Tit.</hi> 1.15. Yea they are silthy (in part, though not wholy) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter believing, till death: for though God gives faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. and <hi>by faith purifies the heart, Act.</hi> 15.9. and from thence purity proceed's to the outward man, <hi>Psal.</hi> 37. Yet, in this life this is but in part, and by degrees; not Perfectly, but so as that wee neede still farther cleansing from all filthynesse of flesh and spirit, 2 Cor. 7.1, 2. therefore believing <hi>David</hi> saith here, <hi>purge me and I shall be cleane, wash me and I shall be whiter then Snow:</hi> and to believers it's said, <hi>hee is Just and mercyfull to for give, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousnesse,</hi> 1, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. and <hi>if any sin, we have an advocate, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> But it is saide to believers, <hi>but yee are washt, but yee are sanctified, Cor.</hi> 6.11. and they can say, <hi>who hath loved us, and washed us from our sins in his owne bloud, ver.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ans.</hi> God doth by saith purifie, <hi>Act.</hi> 15, 9. hee doth wash and clense through the word, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.26. but so, as that they need farther washing before they be as white as Snow; as believing <hi>David</hi> shall witnesse.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The effects that befall mans being thus filthy, are these; 1. a separation from God, <hi>Esa.</hi> 59.2. <hi>your Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have separated between you and your God, and your sins have hid his face from you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Another effect is, the with-holding of good things; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.25. <hi>your Iniquities have turned away these things your sin; have hindred good things from you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A 3. effect is the participation of all evell; as (fear full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) <hi>sinners in zion are affraid, feare is come upon the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119974:9"/>Esa.</hi> 33.14. <hi>I heard thy voice in the garden, and was afraid, Gen.</hi> 3.10. also sicknesse, <hi>for this cause ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are sick and weake,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. also wearinesse and Paine in labouring; the mans getting his bread in the sweat of his browe; and the womans bringing forth chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in sorrow; and at last the returning of both to the dust; are all the effects of sin, Gen. 3.16. In a word, all miseries, distresses, or calamities whatsoever, while wee live, and at last death it self, are all the effects of sinne; <hi>man suffers for his sin, Lam.</hi> 3.19. death passeth over all, in as much as all have sinned, Rom. 5.12.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Applycation, first from hence wee learn not to mutter at the greatest crosses or <hi>afflictions</hi> that may befal us, <hi>why should the man that is yet alive complain,</hi> man suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers for his sin, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.19. rather lethim whose afflictions hath not yet killed him, say (even under the heaviest stroke) he chideth not alwayes, nor keepeth all our faultes (exactly) in memory; nor afflicts us as wee deserve <hi>Psal.</hi> 103.9, 10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This may serve to abase, or lay us low; <hi>vaine man</hi> would be wise, though man new borne is like the wilde Asse Colt, <hi>Job.</hi> 11.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From hence every believer may take notice of the exceeding richnesse of the love of God; and the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vertue of the blood of Christ; in that persons so filthy should be first predestinated, then called, and after this Justified and Gloryfied.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Our being thus filthy, yea in part while wee live, it declareth the continuall need we have of fresh washing, and of our <hi>Advocates</hi> Interceeding, 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1, 2. and that we need to our dying-day to presse after farther Sanctity, in Soul and body, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18.14. And so much for the First Observation.</p>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119974:10"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III The Second Observation.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is God only that cleanseth People from this filth, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly, or Perfectly.</hi> In which I shall declare these Nine particulars:</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That Man cannot Compleatly Cleanse himself.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That God doth cleanse People Compleatly.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Whom God doth Cleanse Compleatly from this filth.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. What it is to be Cleansed Compleatly.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Wherein.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Wherewith God doth Cleanse People Compleatly.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. What the Companions of Compleate Cloansing are.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. When God Cleanseth Compleatly.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. What we may Learn from this Doctrine of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Cleansing.</p>
                     <p>First, Man cannot Compleatly Cleanse himself from this filth; for Regeneration, which is but the Birth of the Spirit, or the begining of compleate Cleansing, is not of Bloud, nor of the will of the Flesh, nor of the will of Man; but of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Who can say I have made my heart Cleane, or I am Clean from my sin? Prov.</hi> 20.9. though man wash himself in Snow Water, and take much Sope (use his utmost indeavours) yet Gods pure Eye will finde him filthy, <hi>Job.</hi> 9.28.29.30. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.22.</p>
                     <p>Object. <hi>David did Cleanse himselfe;</hi> also, <hi>God bids man make himself Clean, Esa.</hi> 1.16.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An.</hi> But David could not Wash himself throughly, <hi>Ʋer.</hi> 2. neither could he, or those here called upon, make themselves <hi>as White as Snow, Psal.</hi> 57.7, <hi>Esa.</hi> 1.18.</p>
                     <div n="2" type="particular">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119974:10"/>
                        <head>The Second Particular.</head>
                        <p>God can, and will Cleanse People from all this filth, Compleatly, or perfectly; for he cleanseth the whole man from all sin, and that for ever.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. He Cleanseth the whole Man, even Soul and body; he purgeth and washeth too; as here: he makes the inside clean, and the outside as white as Snow. He taketh away iniquity, and cleanseth sin, <hi>Isay.</hi> 6.7. therefore <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires God to sanctifie the <hi>Thessolonians throughout,</hi> that their whole spirit soul and body may be blamelesse, <hi>&amp;c</hi> 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.25.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He also cleanseth from all sinne, I will (saith he to his people) powre cleane water upon you, and yee shall be clean, yea, from all your filthines, and from all your Idols will I cleanse you. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. the bloud of Christ cleanseth us from all our sinnes. 1 Iohn 1.7. he maketh his cleansed ones glorious without spot or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish or any such thing. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. He cleanseth durably, his cleansed ones shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver desile themselves any more, neither with their Idols, nor with their detestable things, nor with any of their transgressions: for God will save and cleanse them. <hi>Eze.</hi> 37.23. as God will not depart from them in ceasing to doe them good, so he will put his feare in them, that they shall not depart from him. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23: 40.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="particular">
                        <head>The third particular.</head>
                        <p>Thirdly, the people whom God will compleatly cleanse are Israel, he will redeem Israel from his iniquities, <hi>Psal.</hi> 130.8. Christs people: he shall save his people from their sinnes: <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. thus in gener all: more particularly they that believe, and repent, are they that shall be compleatly cleansed from their filth: look unto me (saith
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119974:11"/>Christ, all the ends of the earth, and ye shall be saved: <hi>Esay.</hi> 45.22. believe on the Lord Jesus and thou shalt be saved, Acts 16. saved from what? Namely, from their sinnes; for his name is called Saviour, because he saves his people from their sinnes, Mat. 1.21. and this is that that all the Prophets withesse to, that through his name whosoever believes in him shall receive remission of sins, Acts 10.43. be it known unto you, that through his name is preached unto you the forgivenesse of sins, yea, by him all that believe in him are justified from al things from which ye could not be justified by the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> Acts 13.37, 38. Repent that your sins may be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out: Acts 3.19. Him hath God exalted with his right hand, to be a prince and Saviour: for to give to Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael repentance and forgivenesse of sinnes: Acts 5.31. that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in his Name. Luke 24.47.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="particular">
                        <head>The fourth Particular.</head>
                        <p>This compleat cleansing from the filth of sin is, an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter destruction to sin, or a stripping sin off its being: sin hath no being in one that is compleatly cleansed: and where, or in whom sin is, there is not this cleansing compleated: sin being nothing but filth: so far as sin hath a being, so far short is this cleansing of being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, yea, there is in compleat cleansing these six p<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ticulars.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. The subduing. 2. Taking away. 3. To a vast di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. 4. The destroying. 5. The loosing. 6. The ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forgetting of sin.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. The subduing, sin is brought under and queld, in the cleansed party. Mich. 7.19.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The taking of it away from the party cleansed;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119974:11"/>they are separated the one from the other: the cleansed party I say is separated from his sins, and his sins are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from him.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. They are separated from him, as for our transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, thou shalt purge them away: Psalm 65.3. thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity shall be taken away, and thy sinne purged: Esay. 6.7. Also the cleansed party is separate from his sinnes, the bloud of Christ cleanseth us from all our sinnes: 1. Iohn 1.7. and he is faithfull and just to forgive, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousnesse, ver. 9. who hath loved us and washed us from our sinnes in his bloud: ver. 1.5.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The cleansed party and his sins are not barely se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate one from the other, but at as far a distance from each other as the East is from the West. Psalm 103.12.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. This compleat cleansing is sins destruction, for, for this cause the Sonne of God was manifested, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the workes of the Devill: 2. Iohn 3.8. which workes of the devill, is sin. Iohn 8.41, 44.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. The sinnes of a party cleansed, are lost, though they be sought for, there shall be none, or searcht after they shall not be found. Ier. 50.20.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. They are forgotten, or quite out of mind: the cleansed ones shall have their sins and iniquities remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred no more: Ier. 31. as in the party, so also in Gods Register they are (when once purged away) as if they had never been.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="particular">
                        <head>The fift Particular.</head>
                        <p>That wherein God cleanseth, is the bloud of Christ; and washt us from our sinnes in his bloud: ver. 1.5. and have washt their long Robes, and made them white in the bloud of the Lamb: <hi>ver.</hi> 7.14. the bloud of Christ
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119974:12"/>cleanseth us from all sin: 1. <hi>John</hi> 1.7. this is the fountain alwaies open for sin and for uncleannesse, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13. without spilling of bloud is no remission. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. even Christs bloud. <hi>ver.</hi> 27.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="particular">
                        <head>The sixt Particular.</head>
                        <p>Sixtly, that wherewith or whereby he cleanseth, is in part his word and Ordinances, Now are ye clean thnough the word which I have spoken to you, saith Christ, <hi>John</hi> 15.3. Sanctifie them with thy truth, thy word is truth, <hi>John</hi> 17.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>7. That he might sanctifie and cleanse it by the washing of water through the word: <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26. But compleatly by his Spirit, but yee are washed, but yee are sanctified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the name of our Lord Iesus, and by the Spirit of our God: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. I will powre clean water upon you, and yee shall be clean, yea, from all your filthinesse, and from all your Idols will I cleanse you; a new heart I will gvie you, and a new spirit will I put in you, I will take away the stony heart, out of your body, and give you a heart of flesh; I will put my Spirit within you, and cause you to walke in my Statutes, and ye shall keepe my judgements and doe them. <hi>Eze.</hi> 36.25, 26, 27.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="particular">
                        <head>The seventh Particular.</head>
                        <p>The companions of compleat cleansing, are;</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Forgivenesse; this compleat cleansing of sinne, and pardon for sin, goe hand in hand together: The iniquity of Israel shall be sought for, and there shall be none, and the sinnes of Iudah, but shall; not be found; for I will (saith God) pardon those whom I reserve:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119974:12"/>
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.20. yea (saith God) I will cause their captivity to return, and build them as at first, and I will cleanse them from all their iniquities, whereby they have sinned against me, and pardon all their iniquities, whereby they have sinned against me, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.8.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Justification is another companion of sins clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: all the lookers upon Christ shall be saved (to wit from sin, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. And then shall one say, surely in the Lord have I righteousnesse, and strength; to him shall all come: yea in the Lord shall all the seed of Israel be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and shall glory, <hi>Esa.</hi> 45.22.24.25. See further in <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. A third companion of compleat cleansing is, a perfect enjoyment of God: God will to his cleansed ones be a God; and they shall be his people, God in a promise touching his people, saith, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.23. I will save them and cleanse them: so they shall be my people, and I wil be their God.</p>
                        <p>God hath to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, oft times promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be their God; and he here tels us how it shall be brought to passe: namely thus, he will save and cleanse them: and so they shall be his People, and he will be their God. While they are under a promise of cleansing, they have God to be their God, in a promise; and when their cleansing is accomplisht, God is their God in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment.</p>
                        <p>And this enjoying of God for our God, (not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, but in accomplishment) hath included in it these three things. A perfect knowledge of God, perfect soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety with God: and perfect propriety, or interest in God.</p>
                        <p>First, the knowledge of God, when the new Covenant is accomplisht, and God is our God, not remembring our sinnes; then shal we not need to be taught to know God, for we all shall know him from the least to the greatest, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31, 32, 33. yea, we shall know as we are known. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</p>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119974:13"/>
                        <p> Secondly, we shall be present with God, and have his presence with us, when God is our God, his Sanctuary and Tabernacle shall be with us, and <hi>David</hi> shall be our Prince, for evermore, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37, 25, 26.27. when our long Robes are made white in the Bloud of the Lambe; then shall we be before the Throne of God, and serve him day and night in his Temple; and be will dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14, 15.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We shall have interest and propriety in him, for as in generall he shall be our God, so more particularly he shall be our portion, <hi>Psal.</hi> 16. our Husband, our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When he Predestinated us to be without blame, he Predestinated us also to be Adopted, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4.5. Sonship and purity go together; when he accomplisheth the one, he accomplisheth the other also.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. A fourth companion of compleate cleansing is, a perfect freedom from all evill; and a perfect enjoyment of all good: Sin only hinders good things from us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.25. and sinne only procures all evills, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39. When sinne is done away, then there remaines no sicknesse, no aches, no paines; as <hi>Psal.</hi> 103.3. <hi>Esa.</hi> 33.24. no more hunger, nor thirst, nor scorching with heat: but being washt in the bloud of the Lambe, the Lambe will govern them, and lead them to the lively fountaines of water; and God will wipe all tears from their eies, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. No more death, for sinne is the sting of death, and that being done away; then with tryumph shall we say: O death where is thy sting: O grave where is thy victory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54. God will then upon his Mountaine, for all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, make a feast of fat things, full of Marrow; and of Wines fined, and purified: And destroy the covering and veile that is spread upon all Nations: and destroy death for ever, wipe all teares from all faces; and take away the rebuke of his people; and in that day, they shall say: Lo, this is our God, we have waited for him; and he hath sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119974:13"/>us: this is our Lord, we have waited for him; and we will be joyfull in his salvation, <hi>Esa.</hi> 25.6.7. Then shall be sung in the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> wee have a strong City: God hath set Salvation for Walls and Bulwarkes, <hi>Esa.</hi> 26.1. When God comes to save (to wit, from sin) blind eies shall be enlightned, deafe eares opened, the lame shall leape, the dumbe shall fing, the dry ground shall have springs of water; then, there shall be a path called holy; wherein, the simplest shall not erre: but the polluted shal not enter into it: neither noisome beasts; but therein the redeemed shall walke: yea, the redeemed shall come to Zion with praise, and everlasting Joy shall be upon their heads: they shall obtaine Joy, and gladnesse; and sorrow, and mourning shall flie away, <hi>Esa.</hi> 35. chap: And saith God in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. I will deliver you from all your filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and call for Corn and encrease it; and lay no more samin upon you: but will multiply the fruit of the Trees, and the increase of the Field: yea, when I have cleansed you, from your iniquities; then will I cause you to dwell in the Cities, and the desolate places shall be inhabited, vers. 29.30, 33, 34. chap. 34.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="particular">
                        <head>The Eighth Particular.</head>
                        <p>Eighthly, the time when sin-cleansing is compleated, is first, not before, but after the death of Christ; for, first, his bloud is the Laver, wherein this filth is washt away, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. and washt us from our sins in his bloud. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his end in dying is, to cleanse, &amp;c. He gave himselfe for us, that he might redeeme us from all iniquitie, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. marke it! he gave himselse; that is past: that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme; that is to come: againe, he loved his Church, and gave himselfe for it; that is past: that he might cleanse it, that he might present it spotlesse, &amp;c. these things follow; his dying is the cause, cleansing and presenting faultlesse are the effects, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25, 26, 27.</p>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119974:14"/>
                        <p> Secondly, this compleate cleansing is not before, but after their own birth, for every one is borne in sin, <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.4. like the wilde Asse-colt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.12. and 25.4.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, it is not before, but after they believe and repent; for unbelievers are branded with impurity, and filthynesse. To the impure and unbelieving, is nothing pure: but their very mindes, and consciences are defiled, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.15.</p>
                        <p>Also God by giving faith doth purisie or cleanse, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. and therefore compleat cleansing cannot be before believing; neither is it before but after repentance, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. Repent that your sinnes may be (to wit after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance) blotted out: he is exalted to give repentance and remission of sin, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. He gives both, but he first gives repentance, and afterward remission to the same people; and repentance and remission is to be preacht in his Name, among all Nations, beginning at Jerusalem, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, believers are not wholly and perfectly cleansed, no not while they live, as will appear by these considerations:</p>
                        <p>First, death is sinnes wages, The wages of sin is death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, believers used to complain of wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, by reason of sin; as also to pray to God, to wash, to purge, to cleanse, to pardon: witnesse <hi>David</hi> here, and <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7. and many others.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, such praying is according to Christs directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. <hi>James</hi> 5.15. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.16.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, to hold forth remission after believing, or after repentance is Gospel teaching: as he that believeth shall be saved, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. (namely, from sin,) <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. This all the Prophets witnesse to, that through his Name whosoever believeth in him shall receive remission of sin, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. Repent, and be converted, that your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119974:14"/>sins may be blotted out, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. That repentance and remission of sinnes should be preached among all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, beginning at Jerusalem, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, the many promises and testifications pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to believers, that they shall be cleansed and pardoned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth evidence that their cleansing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is not compleated so soon as they are believers; for to believers Christ said, Your heavenly Father will forgive you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.14. and <hi>Marke</hi> 11.25. <hi>Iames</hi> 5.15, 20. it is said to believers, since the death of Christ, He is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and just to forgive us our sinnes, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousnesse, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. and our being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented spotless, is alwayes spoken of to believers, as being to come, and not as being past, to present you holy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable, and unreprovable in his sight, <hi>Col.</hi> 1, 22. He gave himselfe for it, that he might cleanse it, that he might present, and that it should be holy, and without blemish, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.26, 27.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, There is none that doth good and sinneth not; and elsewhere makes a twofold chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to the purest living. First, saith he, Who can say I have made my heart clean. True, may some say, We made not our selves clean, but God hath done it; but cleansed we are, and that compleatly even already; so that God seeth neither spot nor blemish in us: and to such he makes a second challenge, Who can say, I am clean from my sin; who can say, I have made mine own heart clean, or I am clean from my sin, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. Also <hi>Agger</hi> saith, There is a generation saith, they are clean in their own eyes, and yet they are not cleansed from their sin.</p>
                        <p>Seventhly and lastly, that sin is not washt away or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted wholly, or perfectly in this life, appeares by the many promises of remission at Christs next appearing, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. or in the world to come; for there can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119974:15"/>nothing of this nature to do then, if it be not onely in part, but compleatly done before.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> But saith Christ, Thy sinnes are forgiven thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.2. And <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had their sinnes forgiven them, even in this life.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Answ.</hi> These were limited, and so imperfect, and not compleat forgivenesses: <hi>Davids</hi> sin was forgiven him so farre as that he should not die, to wit, at that time for his adultery: but it was not so farre forgiven, as that the childe should also live: neither was this and other sinnes so farre forgiven, as that himselfe should never die; but afterward die he did. And <hi>Hezekias</hi> sinnes were cast be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde Gods backe in this life, so as to have fifteen yeares added to his life, but not so cast behinde Gods backe as never to die. Also the Lepers sinnes were so forgiven, as to have a present cure And the sicke <hi>Iames</hi> 5. might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter praying in faith have forgivenesse so farre as to be healed for present, yet not so farre forgiven but that they were liable to be sicke again, and to die at last: which things are the desert of sin.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, believers shall be cleansed not onely in part, but wholly, perfectly, or compleatly: their sinnes shall be perfectly remitted, blotted out, washt away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and believers shall be without fault, spotlesse, unblameable, without blemish, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not before, but when the first re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection is, when Christ comes from Heaven, and scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Israel is gathered together, and brought to their own land.</p>
                        <p>First, not before, but just at the resurrection of the Saints, for, The dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed, (from filth to purity) for this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible and mortal must put incorruption and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality on; and when this corruptible and mortal hath put incorruption and immortality on, then (sin which is the sting of death shall be quite gone, and this saying
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119974:15"/>shall be brought to passe, as it is written, Death is swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in victory: O death where is thy sting? O grave where is thy victory? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52, 53, 54, 55. In a word, we do carry filth and corruption with us to the grave, but from thence we shall bring none at all: We are sown, that is, buried in corruption, but raised in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, <hi>vers.</hi> 42. Also, not before but just when Christ comes from Heaven shall believers be perfectly rid of the filth of sin, as many Scriptures will evidence, as <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4. Who may abide the day of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is like refiners fire, and like fullers soap: he shall fit as a resiner and purifier of Silver: he shall purifie the sonnes of Levi, and purge them as Gold and Silver, that they may offer an offering unto the Lord in righteousnesse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here is purging and cleansing to purpose, and the time when, is the appearing of Christ, even that appearing which some shall not abide, even his appearing to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as <hi>vers.</hi> 2.5. Again, Repent and be converted, that your sinnes may be blotted out, when the time of refreshing shall come from the presence of the Lord, when he shall send Iesus Christ from Heaven which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was preached unto you, whom the Heavens must contain till the time of the restitution of all things; which God hath spoken by the mouth of all his holy Prophets since the world began, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. From hence note; first, that there is a time for the blotting out of sin. Secondly, that this blotting out of sin is after repentance. Thirdly, that it belongs to such as do repent, and to no other. Fourthly, this blotting out of sin shall be just when the time of refreshing comes. Fifthly, this time of refreshing is, when God sends Christ from Heaven. Sixthly, the same time is the time of restitution of all things. Seventhly, this time of Christs comming from Heaven, which is the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshing,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119974:16"/>of sinnes blotting our, of restitution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is the time which all the holy Prophets since the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan did speak of with one mouth.</p>
                        <p>A third proof is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7, 8. Waiting for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord Iesus Christ who shall confirme you to the end that you may be blamelesse in the day of the Lord Iesus Christ.</p>
                        <p>A fourth is, <hi>Pauls</hi> prayer for the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> The Lord make you increase in love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that so he may establish your heart unblameable before God our Father, at the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ with all his Saints, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.13. from hence note; first, what the thing desired for this believing people is, namely their increase in love. Secondly, his end in desiring this thing for them, namely, that they might be unblameable before God. Thirdly, the nominating the time when such as increase in love, shall be unblameable before God, namely, when Christ comes from Heaven with all his Saints.</p>
                        <p>A fifth place is, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 5.23. I pray God your whole spirit, soul, and body may be kept blamelesse, unto the comming of Iesus Christ.</p>
                        <p>A sixth is, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.19. What is our hope, or joy, or crown of rejoycing, even ye are it, in the presence of Christ at his comming. Furthermore, When Christ who is our life shall appear, then we shall also appear with him in glory, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.4. And so our conversation is in heaven, from whence we look for our Saviour the Lord Iesus, who shall change our vile bodies, and make them like his glorious body, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. The triall of our faith (which is more pretious than Gold tried in the fire) shall be to our praise, and honour, and glory at the appearing of our Lord Iesus Christ, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. Now to him that is able to keep you from falling, and to present you fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse before the presence of his glory, <hi>&amp;c. Iude</hi> 24. These ten Scriptures and many others that might be brought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119974:16"/>in, do evidently declare that the next comming of Christ is the time of the Saints compleatnesse, they are not compleat till then, and good reason it should be so; for,</p>
                        <p>First, their compleatnesse is in no other, or through no other than Iesus Christ, <hi>Colos.</hi> 1.27. and 22.10. and Christ is a Redeemer, and not a preventer, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. And so this compleatnesse cannot be before the day of redemption, which is not yet, as <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.31. By which ye are sealed untill the day of redemption. Neither will this day be till his next comming, or till the Kingdome of God come, as <hi>Luke</hi> 21. We by faith wait for this redemption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, we cannot bear the image of the heavenly, till after we have borne the image of the earthly, and not onely sin but also the effects thereof, even the return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to dust, is of the first man, or of the earth earthly: so that we cannot till after death, even when the Lord comes from heaven, bear the image of the heavenly, 1 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 15.45, 46, 47, 48, 49. <hi>Genesis</hi> 3.17, 18, 19.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, Christ is his Churches Bride-groom, and she his Bride: and the time of his appearing is the Day of Marriage, and then, and not till then is she compleatly trimmed to appear before him. Halleluiah, for the Lord omnipotent reigneth, let us be glad and rejoyce, and give glory to him, for the marriage of the Lambe is come, and his wife hath made her selfe ready, and to her was granted, that she should be arayed with pure fine linnen, and shining, which fine linnen is the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Saints: blessed are they which are called to the marriage supper of the Lambe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, then, and not till then, the new Covenant is accomplished; then God will be our God with us, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119974:17"/>we shall be his people, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.2, 3. Then we shall not need to be taught to know God, but all shall know him from the least to the greatest; now we know but in part, and see, as in a glasse darkly, then shall we see face to face, and know as we are known, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. By <hi>now,</hi> is meant the time of this life; and by <hi>then,</hi> the time of Christs appearing; as 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. It doth not now appear what we shall be, but we know that when he shall appear, we shall be like him, and see him as he is.</p>
                        <p>Lastly, when the <hi>Iewes</hi> even the whole house of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> are gathered out of all countries to their own land, and become one people; then and not till then, shall sin be perfectly purged and washt away: for the proof of this, marke what God saith, I will bring Israel again to his habitation: in those dayes, and at that time the iniquity of Israel shall be sought for, and there shall be none; and the sinnes of Judah, but they shall nor be found, <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.19, 20. I will cause the captivity of Judah and of Israel to returne; and will cleanse them from all their iniquity whereby they have sinned against me, <hi>Ier.</hi> 33.7, 8. I will take them from among the heathen, and gather them out of all countries, and bring them to their own land, then will I powre clean water upon their, and cleanse them from all their filthinesse, and from all their idols, and give them a new heart, and a new spirit, and put my spirit within them, and cause them to keep my statutes, and do them, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.24, 25. I will take the children off from among the heathen, where they be gone, and bring them in on every side, to their own land; and in that land make them one people, one king shall be King to them all, and they shall never be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two Nations or two Kingdomes any more at all; neither shall they be poluted any more with their Idols, nor with their abominations, nor with any of their trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119974:17"/>but I will save them out of their dwelling places, and will cleanse them, so they shall be my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and I will be their God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.21, 22, 23. My servant beloved, shall be their King, and I will make a covenant, an everlasting covenant of peace with them, <hi>&amp;c. vers.</hi> 24. <hi>to the end.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Behold, I will gather them out of all countries wherein I have in my fury driven them, and bring them to this place, and cause them to dwell safely; and they shall be my people, and I will be their God; and I will give them one heart, and one way, to fear me for ever, for the good of them and their children, and I will make an everlasting covenant with them, not to turne from them to do them good; and I will put my fear in their hearts that they shall not depart from me, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.37, 38, 39, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As I have watched over them, to plucke up, break down, and destroy; so I will watch over them, to build and to plant: then they shall say no more, The fathers have eaten sowre grapes and the childrens teeth are set on edge. Yea, the dayes come, that I will make with the house of Judah and Israel a new covenant, not like, <hi>&amp;c. Jer.</hi> 31.28, 29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And so all Israel shall be saved, (as it is written) the deliverer shall come out of Sion, and turne away ungodlinesse from <hi>Jacob:</hi> and this is my covenant with them, when I shall take away their sinnes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26, 27.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> But these Scriptures were fulfilled, when the Iewes returned from <hi>Babylon,</hi> at the end of seventy yeares.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Answ.</hi> No such matter, for, first, that was not a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering from all Counntries. Secondly, they were not then made one people, nay, ten of the Tribes did not then returne. Secondly, <hi>David</hi> (that is beloved, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Christ) was not then their king among them. Fourthly, they have defiled themselves since that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119974:18"/>Fifthly, and lastly, and are again captivated.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> But these places concerne the Iewes, and what is that to us Gentiles?</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Answ.</hi> Though they do concerne the Iewes call, yet it may afford comfort to believing Gentiles, for they shall share with the Iewes in all their priviledges, when he is the glory of his people Israel: he is also a Light to lighten the Gentiles, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.32. Rejoyce ye Gentiles with his people, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.10, 11, 12. Rejoyce and be glad with Ierusalem, all ye that love her; rejoyce, for joy, with her all ye that mourne for her, for ye shall sucke and be satisfied with the breasts of her consolation: ye shall milke out, and be delighted with her glory: for behold, I will extend peace on her like a sloud, and the glory of the Gentiles like a flowing streame: then shall ye sucke, ye shall be borne upon her sides, and dandled upon her knees, as one whom his mother com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth, so will I comfort you, even in Ierusalem, <hi>Isay</hi> 66.10, 11, 12, 13. If the diminishing of them be the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Gentiles, how much more shall their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance be? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12. These and other Scriptures do evidently shew that the Gentiles shall share with the Iewes in glory.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Quest.</hi> Are there three distinct times of compleat cleansing?</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Answ.</hi> No, but the resurrection of the Saints, the comming of Christ, and the gathering and restoring of Israel to their Land, is at one and the same time.</p>
                        <p>First, the Saints resurrection is just when Christ comes, and this wil appear, first, by consequence thus, being each the time of the Saints reward or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence: I come quickly, and my reward is with me, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. Thou shalt be recompenced at the resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the just, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.14. Yea, secondly, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture plainly speakes it; As in <hi>Adam</hi> all die, so in Christ
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119974:18"/>shall all be made alive. Every one in his order, first Christ, afterward they that are Christ's, at his comming, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23. The Lord shall descend from Heaven with a shout, and with the voice of the Arch-angel, and with the Trumpe of God; and the dead in Christ shall first rise, and then shall such as live and remain be caught up with them also, to meet the Lord in the aire, and so shall ever be with the Lord, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 4.16, 17.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, also the Iewes restoration is just when Christ comes; for, first, he comes to restore all things, and this is one of the all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1.6. the Disciples asked, saying, Lord, Wilt thou at this time restore the Kingdom to Israel: and Christ reproves them not for expecting him to restore it, but yields to that, in saying, The times and seasons are kept in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers power, and not for them to know.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, when they are thus gathered or restored; they shall have but one King, and the beloved (to wit, Iesus Christ) shall be their King, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.22, 24.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, the day of Christ's comming is his and his peoples Wedding-day; then the Bride-groom and the Bride come together, as before minded, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. But the believing Iewes are a principal part of this Spouse; for the believing Iew and the believing Gentile (as was minded) share together, the Gentiles being fellow-heires, and of the same body, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.7. But their Wedding-day is, when this their gathering is, <hi>&amp;c. Hosea</hi> 1.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, when they are gathered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the new covenant is accomplished, then God will be his peoples God, and they shall be his people; they shall then know God, and not need teaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when Christ appeares we shall be like him, see him as he is, and know as we are known, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as hath been proved.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="particular">
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119974:19"/>
                        <head>The ninth and last Particular.</head>
                        <p>For application; first, we learne from hence to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish between expective and active enjoyments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the giving out, and the accomplishing of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; and so, between enjoyments in a promise and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments in performance, between the cause and the effect, between living by faith and living by sense, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the time of the earthly and the time of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, the time of the first, and the time of the second <hi>Adam,</hi> between bloud-spilling, and washing in bloud; the time of the one, and the time of the other; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween being to present, and having presented; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween being to cleanse, and having cleansed; between cleansing and pardoning in part, and cleansing or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning compleatly; between God's purposing to do things, and the accomplishing of what he had before purposed; yea, the time of one, and the time of the other; yea, between the time of purchasing things, and the time of redeeming the purchased things: for, Christ is come a high Priest of good things to come, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.14.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, this sheweth the union and concurrence of many Scriptures, which otherwise seem to jarre; as the concurrance of <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.34. I came not to send peace on the earth; with <hi>Psal.</hi> 72.7. In his dayes the righteous shal flourish, and abundance of peace shal be, so long as the moon endureth. The concurrance of <hi>John</hi> 18.36. with <hi>Isay</hi> 9.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32. He shal sit on the Throne of his father <hi>David.</hi> The kingdomes of this world are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the kingdomes of the Lord and his Christs, and he shal reigne for evermore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. The concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>Marke</hi> 10.45. The Son of Man came not to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119974:19"/>served, but to serve; with <hi>Psal.</hi> 72.11. All Kings shal worship him, al Nations shal serve him. The concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>Isay</hi> 42.2. He shall not cry, nor cause his voyce to be heard in the street; with <hi>Amos</hi> 1.2. The Lord shal roar from Zion, and utter his voyce in Ierusalem. The concurrance of <hi>Luke</hi> 9.36. The Son of Man is not come to destroy mens lives; with <hi>psal.</hi> 2.9. Thou shalt crush them with a rod of iron, and break them in pieces as a potters vessel. The concurrance of <hi>Luke</hi> 9.58. Foxes have holes, and Birds have nests, but the Son of Man hath not whereon to rest his head; with <hi>psal.</hi> 72.15. The kings of Tarshish and of the isles shal bring pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents, the kings of Schebah and Sebah shall bring gifts: yea, he shal live, and to him they shall bring of the gold of Shebah. The concurrance of <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.9. Made inferiour to the Angels; with <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.4. And is made more excellent than Angels, having obtained a more excellent name than they. The concurrance of <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. Repent, that your sinnes may be blotted out; and <hi>psal.</hi> 130.8. He shal redeem Israel from his iniquity; with <hi>Isay</hi> 44.22. I have blotted out thy transgressions as a cloud, and thy sinnes as a mist; I have redeemed thee. The concurrance of <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.19. My God shal supply all your wants; with <hi>psal.</hi> 23.1. The Lord is my shepherd, I shal want nothing. The concurrance of <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. Not as though I had alreedy attained, or were already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; with <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10. Ye are compleat in him.</p>
                        <p>We are (I say) to distinguish between the first and second comming of Christ, for the reconcilement of these and many more such like Places: as for example.</p>
                        <p>My Kingdom is not of this world, to wit, not yet, Now, my Kingdom is not from hence, <hi>John</hi> 18.36. But, He shall sit on the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> and on his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Isay</hi> 9.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32, 33. The kingdomes of this World shall be our Lords and his Christs, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.15.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119974:20"/>He shal sit on the Throne of his father <hi>David,</hi> and on his kingdom, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32, 33. to wit, hereafter. When the Son of Man cometh in his glory, and all the the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels with him, then he shal sit on the Throne of his glory; not before.</p>
                        <p>Again, He was made a little inferiour to the Angels, but when, namely, when he came into the world to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.9. But he is made more excellent than the Angels, and hath a more excellent name than they. And when is that? namely, at his next appearing. When he bringeth his first begotten Son again into the world, he saith, And let all the Angels of God worship him, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.6. He hath not put in subjection to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the world to come whereof we speak, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.5.</p>
                        <p>Again, Who made me a judge or a divider over you? <hi>Luke</hi> 12.14. to wit, at his first comming: but, he shal judge the heathen, <hi>psal.</hi> 110.6. He shal have portion with the great, and divide the spoil with the strong, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.12. at his next appearing, and in his kingdom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. And so he came not, when he first came, to send peace on the earth: but in his dayes, (that is, when he comes to reigne) the righteous shal flourish, and abundance of peace shal be, so long as the Moon endureth. And so we are to consider all such like places.</p>
                        <p>Furthermore, touching his ruling over Nations, his having the utmost parts of the Earth for his possession; his having all Kings to worship him, all Nations to serve him, and to bring to him of the gold of Shebah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We may consider three things:</p>
                        <p>First, that these things appertain to Christ, consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as man: as <hi>psal.</hi> 2. I wil give thee (I, to wit, God) wil give thee, to wit, Christ as Man, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. He gave him do minion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He, to wit, the Ancient of dayes: gave him, to wit, the Son of Man, <hi>vers.</hi> 13. <hi>psal.</hi> 110.2. Rule thou, here is the party speaking, the God-head:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119974:20"/>and the party spoke to, Christ as Man: for, The Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all judgement to the Son, <hi>John</hi> 5.22, 27. He hath appointed a day in which he wil judge the world in righteousnesse, by that man whom he hath appointed, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, these things appertain not to his time of suffering, but to his time of exaltation; for, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Dignity. <hi>3ly,</hi> his time of exaltation to his Throne, and seat of judgement, is not his first but second com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; He shal shew himselfe from heaven with his mighty Angels, 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 1.7. And when the Son of Man comes in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him, then shal he fit upon the Throne of his glory, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. He shal judge quicke and dead at his appearing, and in his kingdom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. Thou hast received. thy great might, and hast obtained the kingdom. The Gentiles were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead that they should be judged, and that thou shouldest give a reward to thy servants the Prophets, and thy Saints to such as fear thy Name, smal or great; and that thou shouldest destroy them that destroy the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17, 18.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, this Doctrine teacheth the Saints patience in their greatest extremity; even the consideration that they are in the first <hi>Adam,</hi> before they are in the second; and that they bear the heavenly, after they have borne the earthly; after they have suffered with Christ, they shal reigne with him.</p>
                        <p>They faint not, while they look not on things seen, but on the things not seen, which are weighty and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 4.17, 18. They knowing that the men of the world have their portion in this life; and that it is not so with themselves; but they shall be satisfied when they awake, <hi>psal.</hi> 17.14, 15. to wit, from sleeping in the grave, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2, 3.</p>
                        <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:21"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:21"/>
                  <p>Ancient and Durable GOSPEL. <hi>The Second Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By way of answer to <hi>Samuel Richardsons</hi> Book, intituled, <hi>Justification by Christ alone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherein by X X. Reasons and Answers to XXVI. Objections: he would prove that all the Elect were perfect and compleat, as as soon ever Christ died.</p>
                  <p>And his XX. Reasons and his Answers to the said XXVI. Objections are here unbottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his mistakes are in a measure dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, by plain unwrested Scripture.</p>
                  <p>In Dialogue-manner, wheresn the Heads of every Particle in his Book are written down, with a Scripture Answer to each Particular; and so maintaining Believers perfection and compleatnesse, to be at the appearing of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and not before.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Th. Kilcop,</hi> servant to the King of Kings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> 1648.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119974:22"/>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119974:22"/>
                  <head>Ancient and durable GOSPEL.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. <hi>In answer to the Title.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thomas Kilcop.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Iustification is by Christ alone, I grant, and that he shal take away and utterly destroy the sinnes of his people, and present his people holy, and without spot, I affirme: but that he hath done thus already, I deny; for they are not spotlesse, til Christs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing; but of this by and by.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <div n="1" type="epistle">
                        <head>Touching the first Epistle.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Samuel Richardson,</speaker>
                           <p>These times in respect of errour are perillous, therefore it behoves the Saints to sticke fast to the Truth, the which to do, Let us not deny the Truth of the Letter of Scripture; yet not so to rest on the Letter, as to deny the sense.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilcop.</speaker>
                           <p>I like both the councel and direction very well.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Richardson.</speaker>
                           <p>Some place Iustification in conscience onely, but I place it onely in Christ.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>It is as wel in the conscience by embracement, as in Christ by procurement; and so in both; it is in Christ as the Iustifier, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.11. and in us as the Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Isay</hi> 45.24, 25.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119974:23"/>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>If all thrngs on which our happinesse depends be accomplished, then our Iustification is accomplished also.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilcop.</speaker>
                           <p>This is true, but our happinesse depends not onely on Christs Death, but also on his resurrection, Ascention, and second comming; for he died for our sinnes, rose again for our justification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. Ascended to prepare places for us, and wil come again, to receive us to himselfe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.2, 3.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>By diving into this Truth, I have found that faith doth not justifie.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>Who saith it doth? I take your selfe to be the first framer of that expression: I dare not say that faith doth justifie; neither dare I say, We are justified with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith, or before faith; but I dare say, We are justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by faith, because Scripture saith so, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28, 30</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>That Exposition is best that gives most honour to Christ, and least to the creature.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>This I grant; also I affirme, that he neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, nor needeth untrue or Scripturelesse expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for his honour, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.7, 8.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Faith indeed is useful, for without it there is no enjoyment of God, no true peace, nor right to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>I say so too.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>I have met with Objections against the 147th <hi>page</hi> of my Book, where I affirme, Iustification by Christ alone, and not by our believing.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>Scripture saith, We are justified by his bloud, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. And it also saith very often, that we are justified by faith; as <hi>rom.</hi> 3.28, 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. And can there not be truth in both these? if we cannot comprehend Truth in both, Must we then gain-say one, and so give many Scriptures the lie: you sticke not to your rule in this, but swerve from Scripture, Letter, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119974:23"/>Scripture sense too; but you know, that Christs bloud is applied by faith for Iustification; and if so, then are we justified by faith in that sense, even in respect of appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and if in one sense we are justified by faith (though not in every sense) then are such Scriptures true that say, We are justified by faith, or that we believe in the Lord Iesus Christ, that we may be justified.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Reader, consider things, and take not my bare word.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>So I have done, and so finde but your bare word in this point, and that against Scripture too.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Faith is not a cause or condition required to pertake of the new covenant, Iustification or Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>I grant, that faith moves not God here to, but meer love moves him to give faith, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. And so by faith we are justified, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.1. and saved, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>The Elect were ever in Gods love, and did ever appear to him just and righteous in and by Christ.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>That he had ever a loving purpose toward them I grant, he did in love purpose to make them just, and, in due time he calleth, justifieth, glorifieth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the said purpose, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. <hi>rom.</hi> 8.30. Yet sure I am, that he foresaw them unrighteous, when he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to make them righteous; for he justifieth the ungodly, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.5. and saveth sinners, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. and saveth not righteous, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.13. Sinners they are, till they are saved from their sinnes; and ungodly they are, till they be justified, though not after.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="epistle">
                        <head>Concerning the second Epistle.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>Against the second Epistle I have not much; onely some mistakes in <hi>page</hi> 2. as if we must needs make faith a joynt-partner with Christ, in saying as Scripture saith, that we are justified by faith: and the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119974:24"/>Writer himselfe affirmes afterward, that in one sense justification is by faith, namely, in respect of evidence quoting <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1, 2. But minde Brother, our striving hath not been about the sense, but about the expression; and if we are in any sense justified by faith, then is the expression a truth, and we may warrantably use it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I know not any that will affirme Iustification is by faith in every sense: we dare not say, it is purchased by faith, neither dare we say, faith justifieth. Thirdly, good Brother turne to your proof again, and tell me whither <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1, 2. declares faith to be an evidence of things already enjoyed; or of things to enjoy; the words are, Faith is an evidence of things not seen, the ground of things hoped for. Scripture doth no where give a better definition of faith than here; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this definition, we are already justified by faith, glorified by faith; it evidenceth to us things not seen, it assures us (of what, in reference to a promise) we hope for, We walke by faith not by sight, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 5.7. Fourthly, you affirme as much your selfe, for say you, faith is the eye of the soul, whereby we see what God hath prepared for us. Now to the Book it selfe.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>In your book I observe three things, your mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you intend to prove, your twenty Reasons to prove it, and your Answers to twenty six Objections; o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> which in order.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Unto him that hath loved us, and washed us from our sinnes in his own Bloud, <hi>rev.</hi> 1.5. Herein note five things; first, the parties washed, namely, such as are given to Christ, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.17. Secondly, the party wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Christ.</hi> Thirdly, the meanes wherein, his Blond. Fourthly, the time when, when he died. Fifthly, the ground why, his love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119974:24"/>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>The first and the fourth of these Particulars I except against, and none else. First, you say the Parties washed are such as were given to Christ, that we might thinke they were given him, yea and washed too, before they believe, even when Christ died; as in particular, the fourth you expresse and quote, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. But you need not to flie thether to prove who these washt ones are, neither hath that Place reference to this, but this Place doth, touching this Particular undeniably open it selfe, declaring these washt ones to be Be lievers, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the speech of <hi>Iohn</hi> in the behalfe of himselfe and those he wrote to; and every syllable in it flowes from saith, being the application of Christs love, and cleansing to themselves, and therefore you might more warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have said, They were Believers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>So that this is the summe of all, that when <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> offered up the sacrifice of himselfe upon the crosse, he took away, put to an end, blotted out, and utterly destroyed all his Peoples sinnes for ever, and then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented them just, righteous, holy, and without spot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; for these Reasons.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Sith your fourth Particular, and the Doctrine or summe of all are all one: I shal answer both together, and first, Let the Reader note, that we differ not about the matter what, but the time when spotlesnesse is, both hold that Christ hath been slain already, and both hold the washing sin away, and consequently, spot les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to be by virtue of this one offering, but he holds that the said offering hath already effected this, and I hold that his Death hath not yet effected it, though in time it shal, he holds that all the sinnes of his People were took away and destroyed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and his People were presented spotlesse, unblamable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> even as soon as Christ died; and this I deny, and I hold that he by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Death shal take away, blot out, and destroy his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119974:25"/>Peoples sinnes, and that for ever, but he hath not by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his said Death accomplished these things as yet. In a word, I distinguish between the cause and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, between the time of the one and time of the other, and he jumbles both together: these things were done, saith he, while Christ was on the crosse: his Death shal effect these things, say I, but not before his next appearing. And now for my Proofs:</p>
                        <p>That the sinnes of Christ's People are not washt away, blotted out, or utterly destroyed; and that the said peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were not blamelesse, spotlesse, or faultlesse; nor so presented, so soon as Christ died, neither shal be before his next appearing: this I affirme, and he affirmeth the contrary: if he proves the contrary, and I prove not this by plain unwrested Scripture, then credit him, and believe not me. First, we were not righteous, or fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, without spot, as soon as Christ died; for, He hath made him that knew not sin to be sin for us, that we might be made the righteousnesse of God in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. This is a passage penned by <hi>Paul,</hi> who after Christ's Death was a Persecurour, and therefore this Scripture must needs be written after Christs Death. He that is God, hath made him, to wit, Christ, to be sin for us, meaning a sin-offering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Note here, He hath made him sin, that we might be made righteous: He hath been, that we might be: past in him, and to come in us: he is sin for us first, we are the righteousnesse of God in him afterward: his being sin for us is the cause of our being righteous in him, and our being the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse of God in him is the effect of his being made sin for us: and as the effect followes the cause, so our being made righteous in him, is after his being sin for us.</p>
                        <p>A second Proof is, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. He gave himselfe for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119974:25"/>to himselfe a peculiar People, zealous of good workes. Note here, that our Redemption from iniquity, our puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, peculiarnesse, and zeal of good workes, was Christs end in giving himselfe for us: and when we are redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from iniquity, when we are purified, made zealous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in part; then hath he in part his end in giving himselfe accomplisht: and when his People are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly redeemed from all their iniquity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then his end in giving himselfe for us is fully accomplisht; and his end is accomplisht after his giving himselfe; He shal first travel, and shal afterward see of the travel of his soul, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.11. See a fourth Scripture, <hi>Coloss.</hi> 1.21, 22. You (saith <hi>Paul</hi> to the believing <hi>Colossians</hi>) that were enemies he hath reconciled in the body of his flesh through death, to make you holy, unblameable, and without fault in his sight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Note here, first, what they once were, as also what they now are, <hi>They were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but are reconciled,</hi> that is, they did hate God, but now love him. Secondly, note, who hath translated them, from what they were, to what they are; he, that is, Christ hath done it. Thirdly, here is also minded, how Christ hath procured this reconcilement of their spirits, namely, Through death in the body of his flesh. And fourthly, here is minded the end, why the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement of their spirits to God is thus procured and so farre effected, which is, To make them holy, unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and without fault in his sight.</p>
                        <p>From whence doth plainly appear, that the Death of Christ was then past; the reconcilement of their spirits in part, was then, and their being unblameable and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault in his sight, was then to come; thus it appeares, that his people were not spotlesse then, but it was then to be done. Secondly, neither did Christ as soon as he died present his people without spot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for, Christ loved his church, and gave himselfe for it, that he might
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119974:26"/>sanctifie and cleanse it, with the washing of water by the word, that he might present it to himselfe a glorious church, not having spot, nor wrinkle, nor any such thing; but that it should be holy, and without blemish, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.25, 26, 27. Minde it, he gave himselfe, that he might cleanse, and cleanseth, that he might present spotlesse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Presenting spotlesse is after cleansing, and cleansing is after Chtists dying and giving himselfe. First, he in love gives himselfe for his church. Secondly, he cleanseth it by his word. Thirdly, he after this clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing presents it without spot or blemish, this is the second thing.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, spotlesnesse, or unblamablenesse, is not before, but just at the appearing of Jesus Christ, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7, 8. Waiting for the appearing of our Lord Iesus Christ, who shal confirme you to the end, that ye may be blamelesse in the day of our Lord Iesus Christ. From hence note,</p>
                        <p>First, that these Saints waited for the appearing of Iesus Christ.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, he whom they waited for shal confirme them to the end.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, the ground of this confirming of them is, that they may be blamelesse.</p>
                        <p>And lastly, the time when they shal be blamelesse, is, the day of our Lord Iesus, the day of his appearing: these were Saints already, they were waiters for Christs appearing, and under a promise of continual confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion already, but they were not blamelesse yet, but they shal be in the day of Iesus Christ. Again, what is our hope, or joy, or crown of rejoycing, are not ye it, in the presence of our Lord Iesus Christ at his comming, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.19. Again, the Lord make you to increase in love toward each other, to the end he may establish your heart unblameable in holinesse, before God our
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119974:26"/>father, at the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ with all his Saints.</p>
                        <p>This last Scripture containes in it <hi>Pauls</hi> desire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the believing <hi>Thessaionians:</hi> wherein, we may observe three things. First, the thing prayed for, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired for them, namely, their increase of love to each other. Secondly, his end in desiring this thing, namely, that they might be stablished in holinesse and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Thirdly, the time when they which increase in love, should be thus stablisht and unblameable, which is when the Lord Iesus Christ comes with all his Saints, this is the third particular. Fourthly, neither are they presented blamelesse till then, as appeares in <hi>Jude</hi> 24. To him that is able to keep you from falling, and to present you saultlesse before the presence of his glory with exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy.</p>
                        <p>Brother, I desire you to weigh these Scriptures se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously, and I hope God wil discover to you by them, that though Christ died to destroy sin utterly; yet it had not destruction as soon as he died, neither were we so soon compleatly cleansed from the filth of it, neither shal be til his coming, and I hope you wil ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with me, that Christ already is come a high-priest of good things to come, as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.11. especially, seeing I have so great a cloud of witnesses to affirme what I affirme; yea, and they do all speak plainly, and do not in this point speak parables; and sith you have not one that wil affirme what you affirme; but because through want of Scripture, you alledge abundance of reasons; I shal briefly, and but briefly give an Answer to each reason, that the truth may be the fuller cleared, and things that hinder the embracing of it taken away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Because that was the time which he was to do this worke in.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119974:27"/>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>This would be a reason indeed, were it but as true as reasonable, for I verily believe, that what he was to do at that time, he did at that time, and that he would have washt away and utterly destroyed our sinnes then, if that had been the time in which he should have done it, and he doth not do it til his next comming, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is not to do it, til then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Seventy weekes are determined upon thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and city to finish transgressions, to make an end of sin, to make reconciliation for inquity, to bring in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting righteousnesse, to seal up the vision and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, and to anoint the most holy, and after sixty two weekes shal the Messiah be cut off, <hi>&amp;c. Dan.</hi> 9.25, 26.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>There is certainly more in this Scripture than I or you do fully understand; but sith you thinke you understand it, Answer me these Queries:</p>
                        <p>First, whether the seventy weekes, which is the time of finishing transgression, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be not after the sixty two weekes in which the Messiah was cut off; yea, though seven weekes be added to sixty two, yet it will want one week, which week by the same reckoning is seven yeares; and if so, Tell me whither this place be for you or against you.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, Tell me whither these weekes are weekes of dayes or weekes of yeares, or weekes of weeks of yeares, called <hi>Jubilies.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thirdly, tell me, whither the end of these seventy weekes be not the time of Christs next appearing, for this you prove by quoting <hi>Isay</hi> 63.4. The year of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed is come; which time is in the same <hi>verse</hi> mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the day or time of vengeance, which time of vengeance is when Christ comes from heaven, 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8. Fourthly, Tell me, whither this finishing trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, and putting an end to sin, be with reference to an offering for sin, as if he should say, he should finish of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119974:27"/>for transgression, or put an end to sin-offering; or whither it hath reference to a total extirpation of transgressions or of sin; if this finishing transgressions and putting an end to sin, be in respect of offering, then in such a sense transgression was finished, and an end was put to sin, iust when Christ died; for, His soul was made sin, or an offering for sin, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.11. and there shal be no more offerings, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.10. <hi>chap.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But if this finishing transgressions, and putting an end to sin, be meant the total extirpation of it, or leaving it no more being, (and one of these senses it must hear) then it hath reference to Christs appearing, as before minded; for he that saith his sin is put to an end thus, or finisht in this sense already, is a Lyer, and gives God the lye, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8, 10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Secondly, he was ordained to take away sin and to present us holy, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 30.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, because he is mighty to save, <hi>Isay</hi> 63. <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.19.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, he took flesh on purpose to effect this worke.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, It is Gods wil that he should by bloud-shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sanctifie his, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.5. <hi>to</hi> 11.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, he came on purpose to take away sin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>These five are Truths, but not reasons, for with what reason wil it appear, that we are saved already, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is mighty to save, or that sin is already took away, because he was ordained, took flesh and came to take it away, or that his people were all perfectly sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as soon as ever his bloud was spilt, because it is the the will of God that by his bloud shedding they should be sanctified, or that his people were presented spotlesse, just when he died, because he died that he might do it, reason tels me that things are not done, while they are
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119974:28"/>to do. Do you not know Brother, how that presenting, is after washing, and washing after bloud-spilling, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.25. Yea, that he washeth by his Word and by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. In his bloud, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5. Is not his bloud (after it is spilt) sprinkled in our hearts to cleanse, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.22. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.2. The bloud of Christ which through the eternal Spirit hath been offered, shall purge your consciences from dead workes, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.14. Bloud-spilling is past, but purging thereby is still in use; his bloud that is already spilt, is still the Bloud of sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and doth still speak for us better things than the bloud of <hi>Abel, Hebr.</hi> 12.24.</p>
                        <p>And tell me Brother, what Gospel your principle wil admit to be preached to unbelievers lince the Death of Christ? With what reason can you say, Believe on the Lord <hi>Jesus</hi> and ye shal be saved, to such as are already saved? Or to say, Repent that your sinnes may be blotted out, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.14. to such whose sinnes are already blotted out, or never shal be? for say you, The sinnes of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate never shall, but the sinnes of the Elect are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Were the Elect saved when Christ died, and are they again unsaved since? Were their sinnes took away then, and returned to them again since? If their sinnes were utterly destroyed then, then do they need no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther destruction: and if our sinnes be to be destroyed yet, then they were not utterly destroyed then.</p>
                        <p>Also, what reproof for, or exhortation against sin, can you (since the Death of Christ) give, to those whose sinnes were utterly destroyed and done away when Christ died. How can you wish then to shun sin, because Christ appeared to take away sin, as 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. If their sinnes be already took away, can they be took away, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main too? Or can they have life or being when they are utterly destroyed? No Brother, this is against truth and reason. When God hath compleatly cleansed people.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119974:28"/>They shall defile themseves no more at all with any transgression, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Seventhly, because he was made a curse for us, and suffered the punishment due to us for sin.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>As he was wounded, made a curse, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went the desert of sin for us: so we answerably shall be blest, healed, and crowned with righteousnessē in him; yet he is made sin for us: before we as righteous in him, and our being righteous in him is after he is made sin for us; He hath made him that knew not sin to be sin for us, that we should be made the righteousnesse of God in him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. Marke here, He was, that we should be; past in him, and to come in us.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, we are not blest till we believe, nor healed till after conversion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>John</hi> 12.48.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, neither are we compleatly blest, healed, nor made righteous till Christs comming, this Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse brings healing under his wings when he ariseth, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Paul</hi> and all others that love his appearing, shal then have the crown of righteousnesse given them, which for present is laid up for them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Eighthly, because he hath obtained an eternal redemption for us, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>That Christ hath obtained for us an eternal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, is truth: and the Apostles telling Believers that Christ hath obtained it, yea, obtained it for them; doth plainly argue, that they have it not yet, except by faith in a promise, and not in performance as yet Indeed the called ones, do already receive it in a promise, <hi>v.</hi> 15. Yea, this place saith plainly, that he is come a high priest of good things to come, <hi>verse</hi> 11. And not onely your own quotation, but others also gain-say you in this point, as <hi>Luke</hi> 21. When these things come to passe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119974:29"/>look up, and lift up your heads, for your redemption draweth near, <hi>verse</hi> 28. And when ye see these things come to passe, to wit, the same things, Know that the kingdom of God is near, <hi>verse</hi> 31. From whence note,</p>
                        <p>First, that our redemption is not yet.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that the kingdom of God, and our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion come both together; so <hi>Epbes.</hi> 4.30. Grieve not the holy Spirit of God, by which ye are sealed untill the day of redemption. From hence note,</p>
                        <p>First, that a day of redemption (for the people of God) shall come.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, this Day is not yet come.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, God seales his people with his Spirit the mean while. See further, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.13, 14. Ye were after ye believed sealed with the holy spirit of promise, which is the earnest of our inheritance untill the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the purchased possession, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Note from hence,</p>
                        <p>First, there is a possession for Believers to enjoy.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, this possession is already purchased for them.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, this possession is not redeemed yet.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, Believers do after believing enjoy the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest of it. In a word, purchasing is before redeeming, and things are to be redeemed after they are purchased; the time of purchasing is past, but the time of redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things that are purchased, is yet to come, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers wait for it, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.23.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> But we have redemption through his Bloud, even the forgivenesse of our sinnes.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Answ.</hi> I have shewn, that we have it already in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, and so we have it by faith, but we have it not in accomplishment as yet, We yet walke by faith and not by sight, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Ninthly, because God promised his worke shall prosper, <hi>Isay</hi> 42.1, 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 55.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119974:29"/>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>His worke shall prosper; he hath purchased what he was to purchase, and shall accomplish what he is to accomplish: but if the time when he died were the time not onely to purchase, but also to effect an utter destruction to sin, as you hold, then his worke hath not prospered, for neither my sinnes nor yours are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly destroyed as yet; and truly, if our sinnes should not be otherwise destroyed, or washt away, than yet they be, we should be in a sad condition: and if Christ hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented us before God already, then hath he presented us faulty, and not faultlesse; for if we say, (as yet) that we have no sin, we lye, and truth is not in us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. But my comfort is, in that his worke shall prosper, and therefore my sinnes shall be washt away and destroyed, though they are not yet. As the time of purchase is past, so the Day of Redemption will come.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Tenthly, else Christ answers not the Types; for as <hi>Adam</hi> (a publique person) brought all that were in him under sin and condemnation, so Christ hath made all in him righteous, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>to the</hi> 19. And the Priests are said to make an atonement for the People, and to cleanse them from all their finnes before the Lord, <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.30. So Christ hath presented all his without spot also. Likewise, the Peoples transgressions were laid on the scape-goates head, who carried them away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>I would Types were more closer stook to than they be, and to the first, I reply,</p>
                        <p>First, none sinned in <hi>Adam</hi> before they were in <hi>Adam,</hi> so none are righteous in Christ before they are in Christ. Likewise, as People became in <hi>Adam</hi> by the first, so they become in <hi>Christ</hi> by the second birth. Our first being in <hi>Christ</hi> is by faith. I account all (saith <hi>Paul</hi>) but dung, to win Christ, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. And be found
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119974:30"/>in him, How is that? may some say; he tels us, Not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mine own righteousnesse, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse which is of God through faith, <hi>verse</hi> 9.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, we are in <hi>Adam</hi> before we are in Christ, and so are finners before we are righteous, we are fil<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hy before our filth be washt away. We cannot be cleansed till we are first unclean, That is not first which is spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but that which is natural, and afterward that which is spiritual: when we have borne the image of the earthly we shall also bear the image of the heavenly. The one we see is, the other is to come; the one before, the other at the resurrection or comming of Christ from heaven; for the first man is of the earth earthly, and the second is the Lord from heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45, 46, 47, 48.</p>
                        <p>To the second Type I reply, that the atonement was before cleansing, for saith the place plainly, The Priest shall make an atonement for you, to cleanse you, that you may be clean from all your sinnes before the Lord.</p>
                        <p>And not onely here, but every where in the Law it will appear, that first sin was committed.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, Bloud was spilt.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, besprinkled on the sinner.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, after all this with other circumstances, the parties were clean, and so pronounced. So likewise,</p>
                        <p>First, We are sinners.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, Christs bloud spilt, is for an atonement to cleanse.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, God by giving faith besprinkles this bloud on us, even on our hearts, to cleanse us, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. compared; and therefore cleansing must needs be after Christs dying. And <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.26, 27. <hi>Col.</hi> 11.22. are by you perverted and wrested, in saying, from these places he hath presented, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their voice
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119974:30"/>is this, to present, that he might wash and cleanse, that he might present, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> just answerable to the Priests atonement to cleanse.</p>
                        <p>And to the third Type I reply, that the Peoples transgressions were laid on the scape-goats head, after the slain-goat was slain, and he carried them away after they were laid on his head. Apply this.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Eleventhly, because Christ exceeds all the Priests and sacrifices under the Law, for he makes the commers to him perfect, which thing they could not do, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.10, 11, 12, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.9. <hi>to</hi> 14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>You have from these places uttered a real truth, and as real a truth you have left out, namely, That they that are called might receive the promise of eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. Wherein note,</p>
                        <p>First, it appertaines but to called ones.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, they have it but in a promise.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, by your grant they come to him before they <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>e perfect.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, Christ himselfe is yet in expectation, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.13.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, perfect saving, or saving to the utmost, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend not onely upon the death, but also upon the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding of Christ, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7, 25.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, he is by dying not the Finisher but the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of an eternal salvation.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Twelfthly, because there needs no more offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for sin.</p>
                        <p>Thirtenthly, he hath done whatever was required to make us righteous.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis true, this offering being compleat, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no other offering, nor this again, to make us righteous, neither is it needfull, but yet, the redeeming
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119974:31"/>what is already purchased is needfull, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.14. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise we should have no greater happinesse than we have in this life, and so should be of all men most miserable: but the purchasing is past, redeeming, or effecting is to come, (as minded before) and this is my comfort.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Fourteenthly, because if Christ had not done what he came to do, he would not have ascended to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>In that he came to purchase and not to effect, it appeares that he hath done what he came to do: but if he had come not onely to purchase, but also to effect the taking away and destroying of sin, then the experience of every believer would evidence that Christ hath not done what he came to do, for sin hath a being to this very day: but the truth is, he is come, a high priest of good things to come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Fifteenthly, because Scripture saith, We are instified by his bloud, which could not be, were not our sinnes washt away and destroyed, and we presented spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>This I answer first with the like Argument, Christ having given himselfe for his Church is afterward to wash it, to cleanse it, to make it, and present it spotlesse without blemish, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. which things are not to do when it is once justified, therefore it could not be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as soon as he died: but,</p>
                        <p>Secondly, tis true, we are justified by his bloud, yet not before his bloud is by faith applied, for he is not a propitiation, much lesse justification otherwise than through faith in his bloud, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.26. God is just, and a justifier of him that is of the faith of Jesus, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25, 26.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>As <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.26, 27. Our sinnes are cast behinde Gods backe, <hi>Isay</hi> 38.17. cast into the sea, <hi>Mich.</hi>
                           <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119974:31"/>7.19. Removed as farre from us as the East is from the West, <hi>Psal.</hi> 103.12. are blotted out, <hi>Isay</hi> 44.22. are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ered, <hi>Psal.</hi> 32.1. and not remembered, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>The two first places as hath been proved, speak of presenting spotlesse, as being to come, and not as being past; he did give himselfe that he might wash, and cleanse; and washeth and cleanseth, that he might present spotlesse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> so that presenting spotlesse is after deansing, and cleanfing after dying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to the other Scriptures I reply, Most of them are the speeches of Believers spoken in faith, which faith closeth with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, and is the assurance of things hoped for, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, though they speak in the present tense, yet they are all prophecies of things to come, as your own point denies not, being all spoken and penned not just at, but long before Christs death; and therefore whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther these Scriptures be with or against your point, judge your selfe. And can you be ignorant of Scriptures usuall speaking of things to come as if they were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, all things being already before him, he cals things that (as yet) be not, as though they were, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.17. as, I have made thee a father of many nations; <hi>Babylon</hi> is fallen, behold, he comes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thirdly, the very same People that say, he pardoneth, passeth by, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do almost with the same breath say, He will turne again, he will have compassion, he will subdue, he will cast our sinnes into the depth of the sea, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18, 19.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Now I hope ye are satisfied.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>And I hope that when you have weighed your Scriptures better, God may satisfie you with the proper sense thereof.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Sixteenthly, because they are holy and without spot, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.7. <hi>rev.</hi> 14.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.27, 27.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119974:32"/>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>This Reason hath neither truth nor reason in it; not truth, for the time of spotlesnesse is not yet, as hath often been proved: and he that dares with reference to time present say, he is spotlesse, or without sin, is a lyar, <hi>&amp;c. John</hi> 1.8.10. Also it is without reason to say, Our sinnes are washed, and we are without spot, because we are holy and without spot. Again, further minde,</p>
                        <p>First, that often quoting the same Scriptures, will make a volume the bigger.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that as oft as you quote, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>&amp; Ephes.</hi> 5.26, 27. You do and will (it seemes) render it present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though these places render themselves thus, To present, or that he might cleanse, that he might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I also give you further to note, that she that is all fair and spotlesse, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.7. is the whole Spouse of Christ. Some without others shall not be made perfect, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.40. Though he is now a perfecting, we shall not be a perfect man, till all meet together, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.12, 13. And our being already come to mount Sion, to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral assemble of the first borne, written in Heaven, to God judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect; as in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. is but by faith in promise; for in this present life, We walke by faith not by sight, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Seventeenthly, because we are without sin; for as he is, so are we in this world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17. and that is without sin, for in him is no sin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5. and thus (as we are in Christ) we are, his righteousnesse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ours, but in our selves we are not thus, no not after believing, and therefore believing made us not so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis true, that in him is no sin, that is, he never committed any; and it is as true, that we are not in this sense without sin, but in many things sin all, and if we say we have no sin we lye, as ye in your words affirme; and yet you dare alledge 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5. In him is no sin;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119974:32"/>to open 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17. As he is, so are we in this world.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, and as we are not in this world like him in this sense, to wit, to be as clear from acting sin as he is: so neither are we in your other sense, (in having his righteousnesse made ours, like him: for, tell me, Whose righteousnesse was imputed to him, or made his? if no bodies, then what likenesse can there be between Christ and us, in this sense? Truly none at all: so then, like Christ, we (yet) are not in not sinning, for he never did sin, no not in word, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3. But we even all of us do sin, in many things, <hi>James</hi> 2. And like him by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we are not, for he was made his righteousnesse, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 1.31. But there was no body made his righteousnesse.</p>
                        <p>But in the third place, as it cannot bear either of your two senses. I will tell you what sense it will bear, As he is, so are we in this world, that is, Christ hath not in him the least specke of sin: he is altogether fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, and we shall when he appeares be faultlesse and unblamable also, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7, 8. And in a promise, and by our applying it by faith we are so already, even while we are in this world, our hope as an Anchor is already within the vail, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6. Faith already layeth hold on the eternal life and perfection, as hath oft been minded; and this sense crosseth neither Scripture nor reason, but the other crosse both: and for saying believing makes us not without sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We do not say it doth, nor know any beside your selfe use such an expression: yet this I dare affirme, that God doth purifie our hearts by faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Eighteenthly, because Christ hath done, what ever was needfull to do, to make and present us perfect, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>He hath done what ever was need<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>full to make or present us perfect, in respect of purchase, but he <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uth not as yet done what ever he shall do to effect the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119974:33"/>things purchased: things that are already purchased are yet to be redeemed, as before declared, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.15. and this your own quotation verifies, saying, By his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge shall my righteous servant justifie many, for he shall bear their iniquities, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.11. Bearing iniquity is the cause, justification is the effect. He first beares ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and afterward by vertue thereof justfieth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Ninteenthly, because Scripture saith, He hath washt away our sinnes, <hi>rev.</hi> 1.5. He was manifest to take away our sinnes, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. But he came not to do it if it be still to do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>First, these last reasons are included in the 4, 5, &amp; 6. and the answer to them might serve these. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that in <hi>rev.</hi> 1.5. is the speech of faith.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, it is in that place evident, that this wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is after we are filthy</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, after bloud-spilling; for this washing is in his bloud.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, that though it may be begun, yet it is not compleated while the least specke of sin, or least measure of sinning remaines about us, for it is a washing us from our sinnes.</p>
                        <p>Also the other place 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. doth plainly evidence Christs manifestation to be the cause, and taking sin away to be the effect, and so to follow it, for saith that Text, Ye know that he was manifested, that he might take away our sinnes. Minde here Brother, how the real voyce of faith in the believer doth distinguish between the time of Christs manifestation, and the time of sinnes being took away, though you jumble both together; the voyce of faith speakes of the one as past; He was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested, and of the other as yet to come, That he might take away our sinnes: and when it doth speak in the present tense, as if already effected, then it hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to what is done already in part, and what is already
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119974:33"/>perfected in a promise, and already enjoyed by faith, as in <hi>rev.</hi> 1.5. but now minded, and thus Brother you see, that your own quotations are directly contrary to what you quote them for.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Twentiethly and lastly, because Christ saith, It is finished, <hi>John</hi> 17.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.28, 30.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Christ did indeed utter these words, It is finisht. Did he say, The destruction of sin was finisht? or Did he say, Our justification was finisht? No, he did not: or Could he mean so? No, he could not.</p>
                        <p>First, he could not meane sinnes destruction, or total riddance, for He hath appeared, that is past, That he might take sin away, or that he might destroy the workes of the devil, that is to come.</p>
                        <p>Neither did he mean our justification; for though He died for our finnes, he rose again for our justification, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.</p>
                        <p>But that which Christ said he had finisht, <hi>John</hi> 17. was his declaring the Name of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that which he said was finisht, in <hi>John</hi> 19. is that Scripture, In my thirst they gave me vineger to drinke; for saith the Text, Jesus knowing the performance of all things, (to this intent) that the Scripture might be fulfilled, did say, I thirst, whereupon, they gave him vineger; and Christ having once tasted it, saith, It is finisht, to wit, that Prophecie, it was now accomplisht: but one Scripture saith, They shal look on him whom they have persecuted; and this Scripture was not then finished; for Christ was pierced afterward, and this looking on him is after his being pierced. Also, one Scripture was accomplished or finished at Christs Birth, to wit, <hi>Isay</hi> 14. Behold, A Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin shall conceive and bear a Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, and divers were, and shall be fulfilled time after time: and those that foretell our compleatnesse shall also be finished in Gods time, and not before.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119974:34"/>
                     <head>Objections revived, and Answers abated. CHAP. VI.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thomas Kilcop.</speaker>
                        <p>HAving finished your Reasons, you answer Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which Objections and Answers I endeavour to weigh, and to revive such Objections as are sutable to Scripture, and to dis-own such as are not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <div n="1" type="objection">
                        <head>The first Objection.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> We were not justified when Christ was on the Crosse, for he rose again for our justification, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>The Answer</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>If Christs resurrection justifies us, then faith doth not.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, his resurrection justified himselfe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.17, 18.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, his resurrection declares believers to be just.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>The Objection revived.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>First, this Obiection doth not say Faith justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.25. being the place quoted by the Obiectour, and by you answered, doth not say, that he rose again for his own iustification, but for ours.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, neither doth that place say, His resurrection declares believers to be iust: but it plainly saith as this Obiection doth, that he rose again for our iustification. Note, observing Reader, how this Obiection is answered.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Object.</hi> 2. If Christ be not risen we are still in our finnes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.17.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Christ must needs rise to fulfill Prophecie, to make his own word good, and to declare himselfe to be the Messiah, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.19.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119974:34"/>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>As Christ did rise again for these ends, so for other ends also, even for our instification, <hi>rom.</hi> 4. and that we might not be still in our sinnes, and so this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection remaines as yet unanswered.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Secondly, sith Christs satisfaction was sufficient it must needs be effectual.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>This is true, and as true that His sufficiency to effect must needs before it hath effected.</p>
                           <p>And the additional expressions (if sin were never ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, or if they were, and laid on us again) are your own.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>What are we the better to have our sinnes laid on Christ, if they be not taken away from us.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>We are the better to know they undoubtedly shall be, though they be not as yet.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, this arguing is but fleshly, like the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Jewes, It is better (say they) for us to be in Egypt by the flesh-pots, but faith, looketh through a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise higher, even to the things that are not seen, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, What are we the better for saying, Our sinnes are washt away, when in truth they remain? or to say, We are free, when we are (as believing <hi>Paul</hi> was) captivated by sin, <hi>rom.</hi> 27.23.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>If Christs death extend no further than onely satisfaction for sin, we could never enioy sonship and glory, for to confer glory is more than simply to pardon.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>To this I adde, that that glory which Christ me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tited at his first comming, shall not be conferred on us till his next comming, When Christ which is our life shall appear then we shall appear with him in glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Some contend whither Iustification be by Christs active or passive obedience.</p>
                           <p>Though this be only a word by the by, yet being a point of difference, I will lend you my light in it brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119974:35"/>It is by his passive onely. For, if the Law be broken, and the penalty for the breach thereof be under-gone, Justice is satisfied, it can require no more: or if it be kept, then is Justice satisfied without peualty, it can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire none; and therefore it must needs be iniustice in God to require Christ to keep it for us, and to suffer a penalty too for the breaches thereof: but he kept the Law, not for us, but for himselfe. That he might be not a spotty but a spotlesse Lambe, that his Death might not be for himselfe but for us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Object.</hi> 3. If sin were perfectly pardoned, Christ need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not continually to intercede as he doth, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.25. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Though the virtue and efficacy of Christs Death be still in force, yet he doth not speak: for,</p>
                           <p>First, he hath finished his worke, 2 <hi>John</hi> 19.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, he is sat down, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.11, 12.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, his stripes hath healed us, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.5. and our sinnes shall not be remembred, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.</p>
                           <p>Fourthly, if he need prevail by speaking, then is there not perfection in heaven, nor in God.</p>
                           <p>Fifthly, then God is unchangeable, to be unsatisfied with whom he did once love, elect and give Christ to.</p>
                           <p>Sixthly, this argues lesse love in God than in Christ to us: but they are equal, in love, and every thing.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>First, the Objection distinguisht not, whither his mouth, or the efficacy of his Bloud, doth plead or intercede, but saith, He still doth intercede: which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues need of interceding. And your six things have not answered this Objection: nay, you both by plain speech and quotation affirme, that his Bloud is of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual force to plead mercy, as <hi>Abels</hi> to plead justice: and so you have answered your selfe, and maintained the Objection. But because you distinguish the sense, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119974:35"/>then labour by six Reasons to shew horrible Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, to follow one of your devised senses; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a word or two to each Reason.</p>
                           <p>And to the first I say, Though something be finisht, yet is not his interceding finisht; but to this day, His Bloud speakes for us better things than the bloud of <hi>Abel, Hebr.</hi> 12. And if we needed not these better things, his Bloud needeth not to plead them for us.</p>
                           <p>To the second I say, That he is set down indeed, but sits expecting his enemies to be made his foot-stool, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.12, 13.</p>
                           <p>To the third, that saith, By his stripes we are healed, and I will not remember their sin. I say again as before, that they are not relations of things past, but prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies of things to come. Christ had stripes at his first, and he heales us at his second comming, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. And the Jewes are yet scattered, and the not remembring their sinnes more, is not till they sin no more. Which is, when out of all countries they are gathered to their own land, and become but one people, under one king, even the beloved, as appeares from <hi>verse</hi> 23. to the end of <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.</p>
                           <p>To the fourth I reply, that as there was perfection in God while Christ died, and before too; so there may be and is, while Christ intercedes. And while we want per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, he is, and will be an Advocate, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1.</p>
                           <p>To the fifth I reply, that the same God that was wel-pleased with one part of Christ Priesthood for us, to wit, his Death, is wel-pleased also with the other part thereof (even his interceding, and so not unchangeable.</p>
                           <p>Lastly, to the sixth I reply, that as God was pleased Christ should die, and he was pleased to die; so Gods pleasure is that he shall intercede, and he is pleased to intercede: and whose love can you say is greatest?</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Obiect.</hi> 4. If sin were took away just at that instant
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119974:36"/>when Christ died, then such as died before him, died before their sinnes were took away.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>First, all the Elect before or since Christ are saved by the grace of Christ, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, none but Christ could save them before, or us since, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, Christ in Gods appointment was slain from the foundation of the world, <hi>rev.</hi> 17.8.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>Though these be Truths, yet all do want the least shew of Answer to this Objection.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                           <p>Fourthly, God did trust Christ for a payment for the sinnes that past before he had laid down a price, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                           <p>It seemes by this Answer that Christ went thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of yeares on the score; a point strange to Saints, and more strange to Scripture; and <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25. speakes no such things. But there are several conceptions from that place. Let us a little weigh it, the words are, Whom God hath set forth to be a Propitiation through faith in his Bloud, for remission of sinnes that be past through the forbearance of God. And the last part of the <hi>verse</hi> are the words wherein we differ; the sinnes that are past, say you, are those sinnes which past, or were committed before Christs Death. Others say sinnes are past, that is, committed, before they are remitted, but are (say they) remitted, as soon as repented of.</p>
                           <p>First, the sense that you give is above all other sad newes to every mothers childe that hath sinned since Christs Death. The scope of the place being to shew how God in justice is a sin-remitter: as thus, he holdeth forth Christs Bloud a Propitiation through faith, and so remits such sinnes as have past through his forbearance, or in the time of his forbearance.</p>
                           <p>Now if this forbearance of God be onely before the Death of Christ, and the sinnes which through this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119974:36"/>have past, be those sinnes onely which were committed before his Death, which God trusted Christ for, as you affirme, What comfort can there be to you, or I, or any that sinned since his Death? for if Gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance last no longer, and if the sinnes past through his forbearance (which are those which are to be remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) be onely such as past before his Death, then is there no remission at all for sinnes committed since; the time of forbearance being past: sad newes I say, to every one in these later Ages, if your Exposition should be right.</p>
                           <p>Also though it be clear from hence that sinnes are not remitted till after they be committed, and that pardon is not till after confession, is truth, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. Yet, that it is remitted as soon as consest, and so pardon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on our confessions, this I deny also. But from these words note, first, God hath a time of forbearance.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, while God forbeares, man sinneth.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, God hath a time to remit sinnes.</p>
                           <p>Fourthly, this time of remission is when sin is past, and Gods forbearance ended.</p>
                           <p>And the onely thing to dive into for the understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Scripture is, to know how long Gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance lasteth, and when it endeth: to which Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture shall answer, that Gods forbearance lasteth after Christs Death and Ascension, <hi>rom.</hi> 2.4. Yea, it lasteth till his next comming, The Lord is not slucke, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But is long suffering to us-ward, not willing any should po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, but that they come to repentance, But the day of the Lord will come as a Thief in the night, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9, 10. Then Christ takes his Kingdom, rewards his servants, and destroyes such as now destroy the earth, <hi>rev.</hi> 11.16, 17, 18, 19. Then his enemies shal be destroyed before his face, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. <hi>verse</hi> 15. &amp; 19. compared, The Lord knowes how to reserve the unjust to the Day of Judgement to be punisht, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.9. <hi>&amp; chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verse</hi> 1.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119974:37"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Sinnes are not pardoned before they be committed.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Samuel Richardson.</speaker>
                        <p>ALl the sinnes of the Elect past, present and to come are remitted. For,</p>
                        <p>First he died once for all, and perfected for ever.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, Else he must suffer again, or we perish, for there is no bloud in faith, and without bloud no remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.22.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25. must be so understood, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will warrant this, and the contrary is to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>I finde in Scripture remission of sinnes past, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25. But these words, Sinnes past, present, and to come are remitted, I finde not, nor any words to such a sense: and though you and a thousand more should af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it, I believe it not. And to your Reasons.</p>
                        <p>To the first I reply, that he doth not perfect for ever before he sanctifieth, also perfecteth not before, nor so soon as he begins it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.2.</p>
                        <p>To the second I reply, that because his once offering himselfe, doth in Gods due time perfect the sanctified ones; therefore they shall not perish, though he suffer not again. Christs Bloud hath purchased pardon for all our sinnes, which shall in time be effected, and faith should have as large extent; namely, to pitch on a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for all sin already purchased, to be effected in due time. But if our faith pitch on a pardon for all sin, not onely purchased, but also already effected, then is it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended beyond Christs Bloud, or any promise in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whatsoever.</p>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119974:37"/>
                        <p> To the last I reply, that whereas you say, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25. must be so understood, Scripture will warrant it, and the contrary must be abhorred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have for these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions but your bare word, and I have already shewen that it cannot so be.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> 6. We are taught to pray for pardon, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. Which shewes that our sinnes are not fully pardoned as yet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>By pardon there is meant the manifestation of pardon, pardon being not to be obtaind in another sense, for there remaines no more sacrifice for sin, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.18. Yea, it must be in this sense, because sadnesse attends sin: therefore <hi>David</hi> after conversion thus prayed.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Kilc.</hi> But consider Brother, first, Christ had ability to utter his minde, he could, and would have said manifest pardon, if he had so meant.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, he now spake plainly and spake no parable.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, he afterward in reference to this expression saith, For if ye forgive men their trespasses, your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father will forgive ye your trespasses, <hi>verse</hi> 15. Which plainly declares thus much, that the forgivenesse he bade them pray for was to come.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, as <hi>David</hi> sometime wanting the manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pardon, prayed for it, so may we in the like case. And as he sometime prayed for pardon, <hi>Psal.</hi> 25.11. so also may we: and sith remission is to come, and comes not perfectly rill Christ comes, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. Warrantably may we till then, pray for it: and so your answer is null, and the Objection remaines.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, there needs no more sacrifice for sin to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase pardon; but we do need a further enjoyment of the pardon and redemption that is purchased, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.14 He being come a high Priest of good things to come, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, pardon must (say you) be meant the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119974:38"/>of pardon, because sadnesse attends sin. But Brother, Have not you all this while laboured to prove sin to be remitted, destroyed, washt away? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how then can sadnesse attend the remission of sin? You have now lost your selfe it seemes in arguing: if sadnesse attend sin, then sin is where sadnesse is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obiect.</hi> 7. Unbelievers are in their sinnes, therefore not justified.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>The Elect are visibly in their sinnes till they believe. They have sin in them; and are also free from sin; they are charged with sin, and free from charge; clean from sin, and yet do sin, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.33. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.8. <hi>James</hi> 5.17. <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Isay</hi> 53.5, 6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Song</hi> 4.7. And this is a mystery as shall and shall not once was, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.16, 17, 19.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>If they be visibly in sin, then doubtlesse in sin they be; and it is untrue to say they be not.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that People should be at one and the same time, free from sin, and yet have sin; charged with sin, and yet free from charge; clean from sin, and yet defiled with sin, is so mysterious or contradictory, that I cannot see truth in it.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, there needs no better unfolding of our thraldom by sin, and freedom from sin; of our being charged with sin, and free from charge, than your own quotation of shall and shall not, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.16. The words pointing at two distinct times, A little while and ye shall not see me, to wit, when I am ascended; Again, a little while and ye shall see me, to wit, when I afterward descend again, <hi>revel.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. So we, have sin, are desiled and charged with sin for the present; but shall be without sin, undefiled, spotiesse, faultlesse, and free from sin hereafter, when Christ again appeares, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7, 8. And those Scriptures which you quote to prove the contrary do clearly prove this: as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119974:38"/>for instance, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.33. doth shew, that Gods Elect are not onely predestinated, but also called, justified, and glorified, when nothing can be laid to their charge. And <hi>Isay</hi> 53. <hi>&amp; Cant.</hi> 4.7. are prophecies of what shall be, and not relations of what hath been. And 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. saith plainly, That he hath been made sin for us that we might be the the righteousnesse of God in him. He hath been, that we might be. The 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17. is an applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Day of Judgement. And 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. speakes directly of the committings of sin; not meaning that we commit not sin, no not at all; but that we do not so commit it as others do. See how your own quotations are directly against you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> 8. Our sinnes are not forgiven before we are redeemed from a vain conversation.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Then they are not forgiven in this life, for every act of sin is a part of vain conversation; then <hi>Davids</hi> were not, yet his were, <hi>Ps.</hi> 51.12. And if justification or remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of sin depend on holy walking, then the Papists do well to teach justification by workes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>First, how come you to hit the marke so right, as to say, Forgivenesse is not in this Life? Did <hi>David</hi> or any other enjoy perfect pardon in this Life, except by faith? Doth not Scripture say to Believers, Your heavenly Father will forgive you? Doth it not say to Believers, yea, since Christs Death, He is faithfull and just, to forgive, and to cleanse us? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Secondly, though we do say, holy walking goes before remission: yet, we do not say, that remission or justification depends on holy walking; neither will it follow, that it is good to teach justification by workes: for God which will give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, will first give repentance to the same People, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. And yet remits not for repentance sake. He that justifies, and saves, gives faith first; and so justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and saves onely the Believer; and yet neither justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119974:39"/>nor saves for believing. Thirdly, we may teach justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by faith though not by workes, For we know that we are not justified by the workes of the Law, but by the faith of Jesus, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. Object. 9. <hi>All are by Nature Children of Wrath.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Samuel Richardson.</speaker>
                        <p>THe Elect are by Nature under a state of wrath and curse, for wrath is the curse of the Law, or punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due for sin; and by Nature is meant the condition we are in by <hi>Adams</hi> fall; all being once considered in him, and by his fall made Sinners, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.18. But the Elect were at the same time considered in Christ, and are not since his Death under wrath or curse, but freed from it, as these Reasons declare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>As you acknowledge, we were once in <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him sinners,; so I acknowledge, that he did then purpose to interest us in Christ, and in him to free us from sin, wrath, and the curse; but as Gods calling and saving us is after his purposing to call and save us, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. He first purposed to do it, and did do it afterward according to the said purpose: so also he had a purpose to interest us in Christ, before he did interest us in him. He had a purpose to make us children before he did make us children. Even as he purposed to give us a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before we had a being. If any thinke this strange, I tell him, It is more true than strange, as a cloud of witnesses might prove: see some of them, Blessed be God, even the Father our Lord Iesus Christ who hath
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119974:39"/>blessed us with all spiritual blessings in heavenly places in Christ according as he hath chosen us in him, before the world was: that we should be holy and without blame before him, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.3, 4. note from hence. First, before the world was he saw our unholinesse. This is implied. Secondly, he even then chose us to be holy and blamelesse. Thirdly, this choice that we should be holy was in Christ. Fourthly, he doth afterward blesse us with all spiritual blessings, in heavenly things in Christ, according to the former choice, Who hath predestinated us to be adopted through Iesus Christ un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himselfe, according to the good pleasure of his will, <hi>verse</hi> 5. Note hence, that God did not before the world was adopt us through Christ, but did then predestinate us to be adopted through Christ, to wit, in due time. Secondly, his then predestinating us, to be afterward adopted through Christ, was according to his good pleasure. But see further and plainer yet, And hath opened to us the mystery of his will, according to his good pleasure which he had purposed in him, that in the dispensation of the fulnesse of times he might gather all things together in one, even in Christ, <hi>verse</hi> 9, 10. So here, first, Gods good pleasure is to gather all things together in one, even in Christ. Secondly, he did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly purpose thus to do. Thirdly, when he purposed to do thus, his purpose was, thus to do in the fulnesse of times. Fourthly, his purposing before time, to gather all things together in time, is a mystery. Fifthly, this mystery of first purposing, and afterward accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the said purpose, he in time makes known and opens to us. See again, In whom also we were chosen, when we were predestinate, according to the purpose of him that worketh all things after the counsel of his own will, <hi>verse</hi> 11. Here note, first, that God in his own will and counsel did purpose all the good that he ever doth to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119974:40"/>his People. Secondly, this purpose was in Christ. Thirdly, he after worketh all things according to his sormer purpose, Who hath saved us, and called us with an holy calling, not according to our workes, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own purpose and grace, which was given us in Christ before the world began, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. So here first, God had a purpose to save and call us. Secondly, he did purpose to do this not according to our workes, but according to his own grace given in Christ Iesus. Thirdly, this his graticus purpose in Christ was before the world was. Fourthly, he afterward saves and cals ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the said former purpose.</p>
                        <p>By this you may clearly see, we were not saved or cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor adopted, nor gathered, nor in Christ in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment, so soon as we were so in purpose, but first in purpose, and afterward in accomplishment; God first purposeth to do, and afterward doth what he had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, as things are not effected so soon as purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, neither are they effected so soon as by Christs Death purchased; for, he died to make us holy, gave himselfe, that he might wash, he hath been made fin that we might be made righteous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Also it hath been minded that the spiritual is not first, but the natural, and afterward the spiritual; and that we bear not the image of the heavenly till we have borne the image of the earthly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Therefore to say we are in Christ, and in him righteous; so soon as we are in <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him sinners, is untrue, We, (even we Saints) were by Nature children of wrath as well as others, (but when were we so?) even then When we fulfilled the Iusts of the flesh, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.2, 3. And the Iusts of the flesh we have fulfilled since Christ's Death, and now to your Reasons.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>First, Christ hath redeemed us from under the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119974:40"/>Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. Secondly, the Law is ended, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. <hi>rom.</hi> 10.4. Thirdly, Dead to us, and we to it; we have a new husband, <hi>rom.</hi> 7. Fourthly, <hi>Moses</hi> Law is not in force; and no Law, no transgression nor curse, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. Fifthly, we are freed from the curse of it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13, 14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>First, these Reasons are of one nature, and make but one in substance.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that <hi>Moses</hi> Law is ended, and of no force, and that we are dead to it, not under it, nor its curse; and that where no Law is, is no transgression; I fully grant: but this proves not that we are even already free from wrath and curse, which thing you bring it for. For, is there no Law but that to be transgrest? or no curse but what that Law pronounceth to be inflicted? Doubtlesse there is.</p>
                        <p>First, Sin was in the World before that Law, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.13. and since also.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, Death reigned before the Law, even from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moses, verse</hi> 14. and so it doth to this day.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, some sin and perish therein, which were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver under that Law, <hi>rom.</hi> 2.12.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, the Gentiles which have not that Law, have to themselves a Law, by which their consciences shall accuse, or excuse in the day of Christ, <hi>verse</hi> 14, 15.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, to this day men get their bread by the sweat of their browes, women bring forth their children in sorrow, and all returne to dust, all which are curses, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. And Believers are not exempted from it, neither shall be till the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> 10. Such as believe not are not justified, for they cannot please God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.5.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Actions done without faith are sinfull, for they should be done in faith, and so be good in every cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.4.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119974:41"/>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>But if God justifie not an action, neither doth he justifie the actor, as your quotation cleareth. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected <hi>Abel</hi> and his, but respected neither <hi>Cain</hi> nor his offering, <hi>Gen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obiect.</hi> 11. Unbelievers are workers of iniquity, but such God hates, <hi>Psal.</hi> 5.11. therefore they are not justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Then Gods love and grace is according to our workes, contrary to <hi>rom.</hi> 5.8, 9, 10. <hi>Psal.</hi> 103.10. &amp; 130.3.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc</speaker>
                        <p>He saves and calleth (notwithstanding) not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our workes, but according to his own pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and grace: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. Whose purpose was, first to call and afterward to justifie and glorifie the said called ones; but first to justifie, and afterward to call, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his gratious purpose; For whom he fore-knew he predestinated, and whom he predestinated them he also called, and whom he called them he also justified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> First, he predestinates, after calleth, and after that justifies the same People.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>God alwayes loved their persons, but not their workes, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. I have loved thee with an everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing love, and therefore have with loving kindnesse drawn thee. See also <hi>Micha</hi> 7.18, 19. Faith is a fruit of love, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. And therefore those mentioned <hi>Psal.</hi> 5.11. are such as are not elected; for the Elect were at the worst in the love of God, and ordained to eternal life, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>First, Sin is filthy, and defiles him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, this distinction perverts this Scripture, which saith, He hates the workers of iniquity.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, tell me what sense <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. can bear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side this, to wit, that God had a loving purpose toward them, wherewith he drew them.</p>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119974:41"/>
                        <p> First, your other quotations to backe this do clear this sense, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.4. speakes of Gods choosing to be holy, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. speakes of his saving, and calling, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his former gratious purpose.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, you speak your selfe of their being ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to eternal life.</p>
                        <p>Lastly, without doubt, Wrath is upon every one by Nature, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.3. and is not removed from any that abide in unbelief, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>rom.</hi> 11.23.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> 12. Such as believe not are condemned alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. therefore not justified.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>All such places must be taken according to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible appearance, and not according to Gods eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree: for, if his will be that all shall be damned, they shall never be saved; for his counsel shall stand, he will do his pleasure, <hi>Isay</hi> 46.10. And if they be damned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, there is no way to escape it. And sith all were unbelievers once, it will follow by this exposition, that all must perish, or God must change his will. For, he that believes not shall be damned, <hi>Marke</hi> 16. But there is no condemnation to such as are in <hi>Christ Iesus, rom.</hi> 8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>That Gods decree shall stand, and that People are past recovery being once damned, I fully grant: but you horribly wrest the Objection, by turning (at your pleasure) condemnation to damnation. Every childe of <hi>Adam</hi> is in him under condemnation, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.18. But none are damned while they live, and so it may safely be said, He that believes not (to wit, never) shall be damned. And yet he that believes shall be saved, though God alter not his will, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, though there be no condemnation to such as are in Christ, yet there is to such as are in <hi>Adam, rom.</hi> 5. Also we are in <hi>Adam</hi> before we are in Christ. 'Tis not the spiritual but the natural is first. After we
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119974:42"/>have borne the image of the earthly we shall bear the heavenly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> 13. Scripture saith, he shall redeem Israel and shall justifie many, <hi>Psal.</hi> 130.8. <hi>Isay</hi> 54.11. But they are not justified before they believe</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>All such places were written before Christ died, and therefore in the Future Tense, but since his Death it speakes in the Present Tense.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>You are shrowdly mistaken, to take all places speaking in the Future Tense to be written before Christ died, for many places do speak of these things in the Future Tense, vvhich vvere vvritten (not before but) since <hi>Christs</hi> Death; as, <hi>Repent that your sinnes may be blotted out, Acts</hi> 3.19. These words were uttered since his Death, even to them that had murdered him. Again, <hi>He is faithfull and just to forgive us our sinnes and to cleanse us from all unrighteousnesse.</hi> Was not this written to Believers, since <hi>Christs</hi> Death, and is it not in the Future Tense. Again, <hi>The prayer of the righteous shall save the sicke, and though he hath committed sin it shall be forgiven him, James</hi> 5.15. The Lord teach you to search Scripture, and keep you from such mistakes.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
                     <p>Object. 14. <hi>People are not justified till they be in Christ, nor in Christ till they believe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Samuel Richardson.</speaker>
                        <p>SCripture no where saith, We are in Christ by faith, neither are we.</p>
                        <p>But first, We are in Christ by Election, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.4.</p>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:119974:42"/>
                        <p> Secondly, the visible Church is called Christ, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. And such as therein are, are in Christ. And a third way of being in Christ I know not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Here are mistakes as bad as the former.</p>
                        <p>First, in saying, We are not in Christ by faith: but if you search and weigh Scripture well, you may finde we are, <hi>rom.</hi> 8. <hi>There is no condemnation to such as are in Christ Jesus, which walke not after the flesh but after the spirit.</hi> Doubtlesse the being in <hi>Christ</hi> here specified can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in either of your two wayes, but in the third, which you say you know nor. This cannot be, a being in <hi>Christ</hi> by Election, before believing, (as you speak) for first all the Saints as well as others were under condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation before believing, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.</p>
                        <p>Secondly the rarest Saints did before believing walke after the flesh, and not after the spirit; as for instance, You hath he quickened that were dead in trespasses and sinnes, wherein in time past ye walked after the course of this World, and after the Prince of the power of the Air, the spirit that now workes in the children of disobedience, among whom we all had our conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in times past, in the lusts of the flesh, fulfilling the desires of the flesh, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. And such were some of you, to wit, idolaters, adulterers, thieves, buggerers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10, 11. Let it suffice that we have in time past walked in the lusts of the Gentiles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4.2, 3. Secondly, neither can the being in Christ here spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified be a hypocritical being in a visible Church.</p>
                        <p>For, first, unbelievers though they be entred into a a visible Church, do walke after the flesh and not after the spirit, Being selfe-lovers, covetous, lovers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures more than lovers of God, having a forme of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, but denying the power thereof, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. They professe they know God; but by workes they deny him, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.15. They have a name to live but are dead, <hi>rev.</hi>
                           <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119974:43"/>3.1. Also, there is condemnation to such, as <hi>Jude</hi> 4. There are certain men crept in among you unawares, ungodly men turning the grace of God into lascivious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, who were of old ordained to this condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Marke it well, <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Christ Jesus.</hi> Also, <hi>They walke not after the flesh but after the spirit.</hi> But the rarest People of God did before they believed, walke after the flesh, and were under condemnation. Also Some that enter into the visible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession (and Church) of Christ, do notwithstanding walke after the flesh and are under condemnation: and so neither of these can be the Parties in <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> according to the sense of that place, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.1. and so it must be understood in a third sense which you know not, namely, a being in Christ by faith: for it is the Believer and onely he That walkes not after the flesh but after the Spirit, that is freed from the Law of sin and death, that mindes and savours the things of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The unbelievers minde and conscience is defiled, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.15. See some more Scriptures, <hi>If any man be in Christ he is a new creature,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. The Elect of God were not new creatures before they believed, neither are hypocrites that are crept into a visible Church new creatures, but when God by the discoveries of love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets in them reliance on himselfe, then and not till then are they new creatures, as 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Such were some of you, but ye are washed, &amp;c.</hi> In the Name of the Lord <hi>Iesus</hi> and by the Spirit of God. Again, We (saith <hi>Paul</hi>) were foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers lusts, being hatefull, and hating one another: but when the love and kindnesse of God toward man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, <hi>&amp;c. Titus</hi> 3.5. See a plainer place yet, I account (saith <hi>Paul</hi>) all but dung to win Christ, and be found in him, not having mine own righteousnesse, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Christ,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119974:43"/>the righteousnesse which is of God through faith. These words contein part of <hi>Pauls</hi> desire: wherein we have,</p>
                        <p>First, a nomination of the thing desired, namely, <hi>To win Christ and to be found in him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Secondly, an application of the said nomination, that is, saith he, first negatively, <hi>Not having mine own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, &amp;c.</hi> And then positively, <hi>But that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteousnesse which is of God through faith, Phil.</hi> 3. Which declares plainly, that when we have the righteousnesse which is of God through faith; then, and not till then are we found in Christ. There is no sonship, nor any receiving of Christ before, or without believing; Those that received him to them he gave power to be the sonnes of God. And who those be, the next words do plainly and undeniably declare, Even to those which believe on his Name. All are the children of God by faith in <hi>Christ Iesus, Gal.</hi> 3.26. This word <hi>all</hi> includes <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> male and female, bond and free, <hi>verse</hi> 28. And if all these are children by faith, then none are children otherwise: and this faith is not <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> but is in <hi>Christ Iesus.</hi> Why is faith termed a faith in <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> but because thereby we enter into him, or have interest in him. Hence it is that these words Faith in <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> are so frequent in Scripture, <hi>col.</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.5, 6. And as Believers are oft times said to believe on <hi>Christ</hi> or on his Name, he being both a Rocke and a Tower, and Believers are by faith in him as on a rocke, and also by faith in him as in a Tower, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. <hi>&amp; Iohn</hi> 5.13.</p>
                        <p>Another mistake is, in saying the visible church is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Christ,</hi> for though the church general be the body of Christ, yet a particular visible church are but members in particular, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 12.27. And though we professingly do enter into Christ by Baptisme, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>rom.</hi> 6. And though this be the being in Christ specified, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119974:44"/>And though Christ joyntly with all his members be called Christ, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 12. yet it will not follow, that any particular or visible society entred into the wayes or profession of Christ, may be called Christ.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> 15. Faith is essential to salvation, for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not say that any shall be saved which do not believe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Neither doth the Scripture say, any shall be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that obey not Christ, or that continues not to the end So that we might as well say, good Workes and continuance are necessary to salvation, as to say, Faith is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>This Objection and Answer are so sutable, that I take the framer of the one to be the framer of the other also. I further reply, that seeing Scripture doth not say, Such as believe not, or that continue not to the end shall be saved; it is presumption in any so to say: and their presumption is the greater, because Scripture doth not onely not say so, but it also doth say other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; as he that doth not believe (that is, never) shall be damned, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. And <hi>Christ</hi> shall come in flaming fire to render vengeance to such as obey not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Also, unbelief is sin, and sin shall not deprive the Elect of salvation, for Nothing shall separate them from the love of God which is in <hi>Christ Iesus, rom.</hi> 8. And if nothing cannot, unbelief cannot. Yea, it is said though we believe not, yet he abides faithfull, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny himselfe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Whom God predestinates, he also calleth, justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, and glorifieth, <hi>ro.</hi> 8.30. And these are his Elect, and though unbelief was once in them it hinders not their salvation, because it is subdued, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that passage 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. was spoken by believing <hi>Paul</hi> to believing <hi>Timothie</hi> in behalfe of themselves, and therefore doth not prove that the said <hi>We</hi> (to wit, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothie</hi>)
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119974:44"/>did not at all believe, for the speech doth plainly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest faith in the speaker: but he and <hi>Timothie</hi> too, were (as well as other Believers) defective in believing, and not alwayes so stedfast therein as they should be: but though it were so, that they were in believing subject, or liable to ebbings and flowings, it is not so with God, he alwayes abides the same. And the drift of <hi>Paul</hi> here was, to encourage <hi>Timothy</hi> to believe more firmely, and not to make him not matter believing. And truly your quoting this place to prove that such may be saved that never believe, grieves me more than all that you have hitherto wrote, for I fear that you cannot be ignorant, that that <hi>We</hi> is we that believe, and that the <hi>believe not</hi> is meant, not so stedfastly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He that believes not shall be saved, he that never believes shall be damned, he that denies him shall bee denied of him, and if we suffer with him we shall also reign with him; for he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny himselfe; though we have ebbings in our faith, yet he remaines faithfull, having promised he will do it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obiect.</hi> 16. God hath decreed the meanes as well as the end, and faith is a meanes.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>That the meanes as well as the end is decreed, I grant, but Christ onely is the meanes of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; justification, or salvation, and not faith. Also there are meanes of enjoying the comfort of it, as the spirit to reveal, and faith to receive it. Lastly, there are ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Gods love and calling, as faith, love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But these are not meanes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>First, I own not this Objection, it not being Scripture-phrase.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, as Christ is a means, so as to purchase, so faith is a means so as to apply or receive, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.12. And where lieth the difference between this Objection and Answer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obiect.</hi> 17. Faith makes us sonnes, for we are all the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119974:45"/>onnes of God by faith in <hi>CHRIST IESƲS.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>First, by faith we know we are sonnes.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, It is not faith but predestination that makes us sonnes, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.5. We were sonnes when we were given to Christ, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.6. <hi>Isay</hi> 8.18. Which was before Christ died, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.10. Adoption is without and before believing, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. before redemption, reconciliation, justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and salvation. True, we appear not sonnes before faith: but to say, We are not sonnes, nor one with Christ till then, or that faith makes us sonnes, is to set faith above Christ, and Christ attendant to faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>This part of this Objection that saith, We are the children of God by faith in <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> is Scripture, and I shall vindicate it: but that faith makes us sonnes, I utterly dis-own. And also in the Answer, are severall falshoods, as, that We were made sonnes when we were predestinated. It is not so, your quotations prove the contrary, for <hi>rom.</hi> 8.29. saith, Whom he fore-knew he predestinated to be conformable to the image of his Son. And also <hi>Ephesians.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 5. is thus, Having by <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> predestinated us unto the adoption of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, it is one thing to be predestinated to a glorious condition, and another thing to be estated in that which we were predestinated unto. Yet I doubt not, but where the one goes before, the other will follow.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that Adoption is without or before believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is false also, For to as many as received him, to them he gave power to become the sonnes of God, even to as many as believed on his Name. Marke it well, it is not said, He gave to them power to know they were sonnes; but to become the sonnes of God: when they believed, they (by faith) became sonnes, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and <hi>Zacheus</hi> became the son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> (when) even when salvation came to him, not before, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119974:45"/>
                           <hi>Iew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> bond or free, male or female, are all the children of God by faith in <hi>Christ Iesus, Gal.</hi> 3.26. They that are of faith are the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and none else, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7. But I confesse, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. is a seeming hold for you, but it is (being well weighed) no reality at all; the words are, Because ye are sonnes, God hath sent forth the spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> Father. Hence you boldly affirme, that we were sonnes before we believed. Except we believed before we had the spirit. But Brother, this will not follow, but it is a meer mistake.</p>
                        <p>For, first, it is true, that Gods Spirit workes faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, as true, that sonship is by faith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, as true likewise, that after Gods Spirit hath wrought faith, and after we are sonnes by faith, that he doth because we are sonnes, send forth the Spirit of his Son into our hearts, to wit, afresh, For to him that hath it shall be given. He that believeth on me, (saith Christ) out of his belly shall flow rivers of living water. And what is the meaning of these words? namely this, He spake this of the Spirit which they that believed on him should receive, <hi>&amp;c. Iohn</hi> 7.38, 39. Marke it well, Christ holdeth forth here a gift of the Spirit, which such as then did believe should receive afterward. Again, Have you received the holy Spirit since you believed? <hi>Acts</hi> 19 And to Believers Christ saith, I will send to you the comforter, which dwelleth with you, and shall be in you, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.17.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, to say, Adoption is before redemption, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, justification, glorification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is likewise false; for, salvation and sonship came to <hi>Zacheus</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. Adoption and redemption come both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.23. And so we see we are children by
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119974:46"/>faith in <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> yet <hi>Christ</hi> is neither below nor at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant to faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. X. Object. 18. <hi>We are justified by faith.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Samuel Richardson.</speaker>
                        <p>BY faith is meant severall things, as knowledge, <hi>rom.</hi> 14.22. Profession, <hi>Iude</hi> 3. Power to believe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22 And sometimes by the word faith we are to understand <hi>Christ,</hi> as <hi>rom.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 16.19, 23. yea, ten times at least in this chapter is the word faith put for <hi>Christ.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>When Scripture useth these words, <hi>The faith,</hi> or <hi>The faith of the Lord Iesus,</hi> it is most commonly (though not alwayes) meant the Doctrine and wayes of <hi>Christ:</hi> but when it speakes of faith as being ours, <hi>Thy faith, my faith, your faith, &amp;c.</hi> then by faith is alwayes meant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief: but <hi>Christ</hi> is never called <hi>Faith,</hi> nor <hi>The Faith,</hi> nor <hi>Our Faith, &amp;c.</hi> no not once in the whole Scripture; and the one time, <hi>rom.</hi> 4. and ten times, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. will not prove one time being weighed.</p>
                        <p>First, by the word Faith in <hi>rom.</hi> 4.13. is meant faith, even beliefe, and not <hi>Christ,</hi> as the whole chapter will evidence; for <hi>Paul</hi> having shewn in the third chapter that God is just and a justifier of him that believes in <hi>Iesus,</hi> and that boasting is not by the Law of Works, but by the Law of faith, <hi>verse</hi> 26, 27. concludes that justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is by faith, and not by the deeds of the Law, <hi>verse</hi> 28. And that God is God, both to <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> justifying the circumcision of faith, and uncircumcision through faith, <hi>verse</hi> 29, 30. And in this chapter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119974:46"/>this thing further, doth instance <hi>Abraham, Who</hi> (before men) <hi>might have rejoyced if justified by workes, but not before God, verse</hi> 1, 2. <hi>But</hi> (before him) <hi>he believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and it</hi> (even this Belief) <hi>was counted to him for righteousnesse, verse</hi> 3. which word <hi>(counted)</hi> argues it to be of favour and not of debt, <hi>verse</hi> 4. And as with <hi>Abraham,</hi> so he mindes it to be with others, Which worke not, but believe on him that justifieth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, their faith also is counted for righteousnesse. And further mindeth the blessing pronounced by <hi>David,</hi> to be in like manner without Workes, and to belong to the believing <hi>Iew</hi> or <hi>Gentile, verse</hi> 6, 7, 8. and so returnes to this again, that faith was counted to <hi>Abraham</hi> for righteousnesse, <hi>verse</hi> 10. yea, before he was circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and that he did afterward receive the signe of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision a seal of the righteousnesse of that faith which he had before the circumcision, and thus he became the Father of uncircumcised Believers, that righteousnesse might (in the same manner) be imputed to them also, <hi>verse</hi> 11. And the Father of circumcised ones too, not of such as are onely circumcised, but such as do also walke in the steps of that faith that <hi>Abraham</hi> had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was circumcised, <hi>verse</hi> 12. And then in the <hi>verse</hi> you quote (to prove faith to be Christ) he drawes up this conclusion from what had been said, That the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of being heir of the world, was not to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his seed through the Law, but through the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of faith: even the same faith that hath been hitherto specified, which is belief.</p>
                        <p>Yea, and yet, hath not done with it, but addes a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for it, because Faith would else be void, and the promise of no effect, <hi>verse</hi> 14. And so drawes his third conclusion, that It is by faith, and so is sure to all the seed; namely, believing <hi>Iew</hi> or <hi>Gentile, verse</hi> 16. mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further this passage, I have made thee a father of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119974:47"/>many Nations, <hi>verse</hi> 17. And that this thing, <hi>Abraham</hi> against hope believed in hope, <hi>verse</hi> 18. Being not weak in faith, stucke not at difficulties, nor staggered at the promise through unbelief, but was fully perswaded that the promiser was also able to do it, <hi>verse</hi> 19, 20, 21. And therefore it (the said perswasion) was counted to him for righteousnesse, <hi>verse</hi> 22. And this he shewes was written for our sakes, that if we believe on him that raised <hi>Jesus</hi> from the dead, our faith shall be counted to us for righteousnesse, 24, 25.</p>
                        <p>From hence note more briefly, first, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles drift in this whole <hi>chapter</hi> and part of the third, is, to exclude Workes, and include faith in matter of justification. Secondly, that he hath (in all this <hi>chapter</hi> with part of the third) to do but with one kinde of faith. 3ly, that the faith that he here hath to do with is <hi>Belief</hi> or <hi>perswasion,</hi> opposite to unbelief, <hi>verse</hi> 20, 21, 22. Fourthly, that this faith here minded by which we are also justified, cannot be Christ: for, first, it is the faith of <hi>Jesus Christ, chap.</hi> 3.22. The faith of <hi>Iesus, verse</hi> 26. Note here how Christ and that Faith are distinct. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it cannot be Christ, for it is plainly minded to be Belief, righteousnesse is unto all, and upon all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.22. He that believes on him that justifieth the ungodly his faith is counted to him for righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, <hi>Abraham</hi> believed and it was counted, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.3, 5. He was the Father of all that believe, that righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse might be imputed to them also, <hi>verse</hi> 11. Also it is that faith that closeth with promises, <hi>verse</hi> 13, 14, 16. and which is contrary to unbelief, <hi>verse</hi> 20.</p>
                        <p>Now to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. in this whole <hi>chapter</hi> and part of the third, the Apostle labours to regain these <hi>Galatians</hi> from seeking Iustification by Workes, to seek it onely by faith in <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> the which to do, mindes them of the dissembling and uneven walking of <hi>Peter,</hi> and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119974:47"/>others in living like the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and yet pressing the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to live as did the <hi>Iewes:</hi> and how he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved <hi>Peter</hi> for it, and that publiquely too, telling him how themselves (Though <hi>Iewes</hi> by nature, and not sinners of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) do notwithstanding believe in <hi>Jesus</hi> to be justified by the faith of <hi>Jesus,</hi> and not by the worke of the Law, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verse</hi> 15, 16, 17. And that himselfe was by the Law dead to the Law, that he might live to God, and being crucified with Christ did live the life which he lived, by the faith of the Son of God, <hi>verse</hi> 20. Yea, and he further tels them That if righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse could come by the Law, then Christ had died in vain, <hi>v.</hi> 21. And in this third <hi>chap.</hi> comes closer to them, minding them to be as bewitched, in that they did not in this thing obey the truth, minding them of folly and vanity, to begin in the spirit and end in the flesh, <hi>verse</hi> 1, 2, 3. and then questions them about their experience in this thing, Whither they received, and others admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred the Spirit, by the Workes of the Law or hearing Faith preached, <hi>verse</hi> 2, 5. And then affirmes it to be with them as it was with <hi>Araham,</hi> Who believed God, and it (his Belief, not his Workes) was counted to him for righteousnesse: and so they that are of faith are his children, <hi>verse</hi> 6, 7. for saith he, God minding to justifie the <hi>Gentiles</hi> through faith, preached the Gospel to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (In thee shall all Nations be blessed) <hi>verse</hi> 8. And this he applies: So then they that be of faith are blessed with faithfull <hi>Abraham, verse</hi> 4. And then still keeping to the thing in hand shewes the impossibility of being justified by the Workes of the Law, because it brings all that are thereof under the curse, they not being able to continue in all things written therein, <hi>verse</hi> 10. And then addes for a further confirmation a third Scripture which saith, The just shall live by faith: and applyingly tels them, The Law is not of faith, but whoso doth
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119974:48"/>them shall live therein. The Law is not of Faith, that is, it admits not of believing for doing, as Gospel doth, for it saith, The just shall live by faith, to wit, a justified life, <hi>verse</hi> 11, 12. Then the Apostle further mindeth our freedom through Christ from the Lawes curse, <hi>verse</hi> 13. And the blessing of <hi>Abraham</hi> to be upon us through Christ, and that we receive the promise of the Spirit through faith, <hi>verse</hi> 14. Then minding how the said pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises cannot be nullified, <hi>verse</hi> 15, 16, 17. declares fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther That the inheritance was not of the Law, but gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Abraham</hi> by promise, <hi>verse</hi> 18. And that the Law was but added because of transgressions, till the seed came to which the promise was made, <hi>verse</hi> 19. And because the Law is insufficient to give life, but brings all under sin: therefore The promise by the faith of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi> is given to them that believe, <hi>verse</hi> 21, 22. But we (saith he) were shut under the Law unto the (revelation of) faith that was to be, <hi>verse</hi> 23. And it was our School-master till Christ, that we might be justified by faith, <hi>verse</hi> 23. But faith being come, (to wit, declaratively) as <hi>verse</hi> 23. We are no longer under this School-master, but are all the children of God by faith in Christ Jesus, <hi>verse</hi> 25, 26. for Jew, Gentile, male, female, bond, free, all are one in Christ Jesus, and being his are <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed, and heires by promise, <hi>verse</hi> 28, 29.</p>
                        <p>From hence note, first, that this third <hi>chapter</hi> hath dependance on the later part of the second.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that the word faith is more than ten times in this <hi>chapter</hi> exprest.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, that the Apostles drift in all this, and part of the second <hi>chap.</hi> is, to exclude works and include faith in justification.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, that <hi>Paul</hi> in this and part of the second <hi>chapter</hi> keepes still to the one thing in hand, and so speakes but of one sort of faith.</p>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:119974:48"/>
                        <p> Fifthly, that the faith here minded is not Christ; for this faith even this by which we are justified, and Christ are distinct; for it is called the faith of Christ, and of Jesus Christ, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. and faith in the Son of God, <hi>verse</hi> 20. and faith in Iesus Christ, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.26. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly our faith in the Son of God, is not the Son of God, our faith in Iesus Christ is not Iesus Christ, Christ and the faith of Christ are not all one.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, the faith that <hi>Paul</hi> here speakes of is Belief, and nothing else: for, first, it is that faith by which we receive promises, <hi>verse</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22. of <hi>chap.</hi> 3.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, a faith in Christ Iesus, <hi>verse</hi> 23.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, that faith by which we live, <hi>verse</hi> 11.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, that faith that is accounted for righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, <hi>verse</hi> 6.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, that faith by which sonship is, <hi>verse</hi> 26.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, its exprest to be <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> believing in Iesus, that we might be justified, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 6. but,</p>
                        <p>First, that faith by which promises are received is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.9, 13.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, the faith that is in Christ Iesus is belief, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, the faith by which we live is belief, <hi>rom.</hi> 10.8, 9.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, that faith that is accounted for righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is belief, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.3, 21, 22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, that faith by which sonship is, is belief, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. by this he that winckes not, may see this <hi>chapter</hi> so farre from calling Christ faith ten times, as that it doth not so do one time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Also Scripture speakes of Workes, what it doth of faith, as, He that believes shall be saved, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. So he that walketh uprightly shall be saved, <hi>prov.</hi> 28.18. He that continues to the end shall be saved,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119974:49"/>
                           <hi>Marke</hi> 13.3. Iustified by Workes, and not by faith one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.24. Thy faith hath saved thee, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.48. Baptisme saveth us, 1 <hi>peter</hi> 3.21. Saved by faith, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.24. And yet it is Christ that doth save his People from their sinnes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>First, these passages, he that believes shall be saved, he that walkes uprightly shall be saved, he that continues to the end shall be saved, saved by hope, thy faith hath saved thee, Baptisme saveth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and true expressions, and will doubtlesse sweetly agree together, when untrue and Scripturelesse expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons shall jarre and snarle at each other.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, none do walke uprightly and continue to the end but Believers, <hi>John</hi> 8.31. Hereby faith appeares to be living and not dead, <hi>James</hi> 2.20. and as we are justified by faith, our faith is justified by Workes, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.22.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, Thy faith hath saved thee, that is, hath laid hold on thy salvation, and we are saved by hope, that is, hope as an anchor pitcheth where salvation is, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.18, 19. Baptisme saveth figuratively, as the same place declareth, and Christ saves meritoriously, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.9. And thus these places will sute together, and each is a truth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>And Scripture oft times gives that to faith which is proper to Christ, as we live by faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. have remission of sinnes, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.38. are justified, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.38. have peace with God, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.1. are sanctified, do over-come the World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4, 5. are sonnes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. have inheritance, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. eternal Life, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. are saved, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>If Scripture do attribute to faith what it doth to Christ, then may we do so too, but it doth not so do. For the obtaining an eternal redemption for us, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.12. The purchasing a People, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chasing a possession, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.14. The being the Authour
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119974:49"/>of eternal salvation, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.9. The Authour and finisher of faith, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.2. And offering and sacrifice of a sweet savour to God, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.2. <hi>A Saviour and Redeemer, &amp;c.</hi> These things and much more of this nature is in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture attributed to Christ, but not to faith.</p>
                        <p>And so we live, have remission, are justified and sanctified, have peace with God, do overcome, are sonnes, have inheritance and eternal life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Christ</hi> as by one that hath purchased, and merited such things, and not by faith in this sense.</p>
                        <p>And yet notwithstanding as the Word of Truth speakes, we live, have remission, are justified, are sonnes, have peace to God-ward, do overcome, have eternal Life, are saved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> even by faith, as by that wherewith each of these, and all these things are applied, and so these are Truths, without turning the word Faith to be <hi>Christ.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Scripture saith, God justifieth, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.33. <hi>Christ</hi> justifieth, <hi>Isay</hi> 45.24. Iustified by his Bloud, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.9. By his Spirit, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 11.6. But by which of these are we justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before God, we conceive by <hi>Jesus Christ;</hi> for,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>I take it thus, God justifieth by Christ, Christ in Gods stead; his Bloud by purchasing, and his Spirit by effecting the said purchase, and all these to be one and the same Iustification, and all before, or in the sight of God.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>First, It was promised Christ should, <hi>Isay</hi> 45.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 53.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Also it is affirmed, that God justifieth, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.33.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>When Scripture seemes to contradict, that is nearest that ascribes most to Christ. Thirdly, the whole voyce of Scripture is to set up Christ to be all in all, <hi>col.</hi> 3.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Scripture sets up God as much as Christ, The
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119974:50"/>Father judgeth none but hath committed Iudgement to the Son, that we might honour the Son, (not above, but) as the Father) <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.23. and though Christ consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as Man, is a while all in all; He shall deliver up the Kingdom to the Father and then God shall be all in all, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Fourthly, all things beside God are but meanes of enjoying God.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, Faith receives but gives not, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. It neither satisfieth, nor merits pardon for the least sin.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, We are justified by his Bloud.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>These are Truths, but they prove not Christ to be above God, but He and his Father are one, <hi>Ioh.</hi> Neither do they deny but that in respect of receit Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is by Faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>We by faith understand that we are justified by Christ, and when ever Scripture saith, We are justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith, by the word Faith is meant Christ, if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly spoken, because faith cannot justifie us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>First, We say with Scripture, <hi>We are justified by faith:</hi> but we do not say, Faith justifieth us. Herein you wrong us.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, when Scripture saith, We are justified by Faith, it doth not by the word Faith mean Christ; for, the Faith by which we are justified, is the Faith of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> and Faith in <hi>Iesus Christ, rom.</hi> 3.22, 26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. It is a believing in him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. Yea, it is a Faith perfected by Workes, and declared to be lively by Workes, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>First, Scripture gives the name of things to the likenesse of them, as the likenesse of <hi>Samuel</hi> called <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> 1.28. An image called God, and the Priests offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings said to cleanse, <hi>Lev.</hi> 30.20.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Is <hi>Christ</hi> but the likenesse of Faith? or, Is Faith a god? and <hi>Christ</hi> the image of this god? For, say you,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119974:50"/>
                           <hi>Christ</hi> is called Faith, as the likenesse of a thing hath the name of the thing: this particular might have been weighed first, and then penned.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Secondly, We are justified by faith as well as by Workes before men, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.24.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>By Workes before men, but by faith before God, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.2, 3, 4. Also that Faith by which we are are justified appeares lively by Workes, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.14. to the end.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Thirdly, because Faith as a relative depends on <hi>Christ,</hi> where one is, the other is also.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, Faith is most for God, and is not the cause but the effect of Iustification.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc</speaker>
                        <p>These are Truths, if we call belief faith, but false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, if we call Christ Faith; for Christ depends not on Christ as a relative: also, Christ is not the effect, but the cause of Iustification, <hi>Isay</hi> 53.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Secondly, Faith cannot justifie; for it is not our righteousnesse nor Iustification, neither doth it free us from bondage, nor present us holy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture attributes each of these to Christ, and we may as well attribute Iustification to prayer as to faith.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, Faith cannot justifie us, because it is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that as well as other things in us is as filthy ragges.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, Believing justifies not because it is a worke, and a worke it is, for the littlenesse of it is reprovable, and we are exhorted to abound therein. It is obedience to a command; yea, every soul-faculty is therein im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. Yea, Faith is a receiving, and receiving is a worke; yea, It is necessary in every good worke; yea, Believers do believe; If objected, that Faith is put in opposition to Workes. I answer, that by Faith then is alwayes meant <hi>Christ;</hi> and when ever Workes are about Iustification excluded, Faith is one.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, Faith in a strict sense justifieth not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119974:51"/>science; but the Spirit witnesseth, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.16. Faith is not one of the three Witnesses, recorded 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. And if Faith could justifie, it would be greater than love, but love is greater, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 13. And we might better say, we are justified by Scripture, for thereby we know it.</p>
                        <p>Sixthly, Believing justifies not, for all justified ones are justified before they believe; for God justifieth sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, enemies, ungodly: and Believers are to believe that they are justified, and that their finnes are pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed already, <hi>Isay</hi> 40.1, 2. Therefore we are so before we believe; and this the Spirit of Truth witnesseth, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.6.</p>
                        <p>Seventhly, because such as say they are justified by believing, know not what to stand to, whither the act, or Nature unacted; if the Nature unacted, then I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, how the Nature without acting can be known.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, how the Nature without acting can be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Faith.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, how then we can tell how, or when we are justified: and if saith can be one houre in the soul with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out acting; Why not houres, yea, yeares? And if the act be not righteousnesse, but accounted so; whither then, God accounts not that righteousnesse which is not; and whither this dishonours not God and <hi>Christ,</hi> as if his Bloud were not sufficient.</p>
                        <p>And if the act justifie, I demand, whither one or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? If one, Which? If many, How many? And if we must continually act, as we continually sin, then we are not compleatly justified yet; neither can we say three minutes together that we are so.</p>
                        <p>Eighthly, the holding that believing justifieth, brings in many Errours with it; as, that God accepts for Faith, and respects Faith more than <hi>Christ,</hi> that <hi>Christs</hi> Death is without effect, that Faith is the cause of Iustification, that righteousnesse is in part of our selves, that Instificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119974:51"/>consisteth in acts of obedience: and so Faith is set on <hi>Christs</hi> Throne.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>These eight Reasons you bring to prove that Faith doth not, and cannot justifie: but you might well have spared this labour: because the Objection which you here Answer, doth not say, Faith doth or can justifie: and so you in these eight Reasons do but beat the ayre. First, uttering an expression which the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectour dares not utter, and then with might and main you confute your own Expression. If it be a Truth, Why do you confute it? And if it be a Errour, (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is) Why did you first frame it? And this might suffice for a Reply to this answering the Objection: for you speak not to the thing in hand, but quite beside it, the <hi>Obiection</hi> remaines still unanswered; and these eight Reasons are quite beside it, for the Objection doth say, we are justified by Faith, and so saith abundance of Scriptures; but it doth not say, Faith justifieth.</p>
                        <p>Yet the better to clear the Truth to the doubtfull, I shall speak a little to them orderly.</p>
                        <p>And the first being spoke to, to the second I reply, that (as you say) <hi>Christ</hi> is our righteousnesse, reconciliation, freer from bondage, presenter of us holy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Faith is not. But Brother, Who attributes these things to Faith? This Objection doth not.</p>
                        <p>To the third I reply, I grant Faith is in us, in respect of measure imperfect, but not in respect of nature, but is pretious, yea most holy, 2 <hi>peter</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>Jude</hi> 20.</p>
                        <p>To the fourth, 'Tis true, Faith is a worke, yea, not onely a worke, but The worke, <hi>John</hi> 6.29. Yet it is not one of those workes which is excluded about Iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for, A man is justified by saith, without the Workes of the Law, <hi>rom.</hi> 7 27, 28. He that worketh not, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his Faith is counted for righteousnesse, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.32.</p>
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:119974:52"/>
                        <p> Also, that Faith which about Iustification is put in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to Workes is not <hi>Christ,</hi> for that Faith opposed to Workes, and by which we are justified, is <hi>The Faith of Iesus Christ,</hi> Faith in <hi>Jesus Christ, Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>rom.</hi> 3.22, 26. Yea, that Faith that is perfected by Workes. <hi>Seest thou not how his Faith wrought by Workes, and by Workes was his Faith perfected; and the Scripture fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, which saith,</hi> Abraham <hi>believed God, and it was counted to him for righteousnesse, Jam.</hi> 2.22, 23.</p>
                        <p>To the fifth I reply, that what the Spirit witnesseth, and the Word reveales, Faith receiveth, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.8, 9, 10. And 'tis safest to say, We are justified by that that the Word saith we are justified by: and though it be not material whither Faith or Love is greatest; yet the Faith minded to be lesse than Love, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 13. is such a Faith as may be where Love is not, and not that Faith that workes by Love.</p>
                        <p>To the sixth I reply, that People before God justifieth them are ungodly, but not afterward, whom he justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he findeth ungodly, but leaves them not so, but justifieth them, that is, makes them righteous which were unrighteous. Secondly, though he justifieth the ungodly, he doth not iustifie the unbeliever, but gives them Faith, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.8. And so <hi>his iustification is unto and upon all that believe.</hi> None else, God is iust and a Justifier of him that believes on <hi>Jesus,</hi> from all things from which he could not be iustified by the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, rom.</hi> 3.22, 26. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.39. And your saying that <hi>Isay</hi> 40.1, 2. bids me believe that our Iustification is past, or that 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.6. saith, The Spirit witnesseth so, is false.</p>
                        <p>Your likeliest place, to wit, <hi>Isay</hi> 40. is a Prophesie, and not a History; as appeares. First, by your own ground: for <hi>Christ</hi> had not in <hi>Isays</hi> time suffered. 2ly, <hi>Jerusalems</hi> warfare was then in being. Thirdly, the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119974:52"/>place plainly declares the time yet to come in which these tidings shall be. Marke it well, <hi>God will say</hi> (to his Messengers) <hi>comfort ye, comfort ye my people.</hi> Tell <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> Her warfare is accomplisht, her sin is pardoned.</p>
                        <p>To the seventh I say, If we do not know what to stand to, you might in love teach us, but this we do stand to, that <hi>We are iustified by faith;</hi> and sith, (as you grant) the nature of Faith cannot be without acting, your distinguishing the one from the other is vain: and sith we stand to what Scripture speakes, namely, that <hi>We are iustified by faith:</hi> though some are not <hi>Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> to tell you, whither it be by nature without act, or act without nature, or both together, it matters not, your distinction being froathy.</p>
                        <p>To the eighth I reply, that these are Errours indeed; but we do not say, Faith iustifieth, this expression is not ours but yours; and so these Errours fall on your head, not on ours; we say, <hi>We are iustified by Faith:</hi> we do not say, Faith iustifieth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> 19. <hi>We are not iustified by Faith alone, but by Christ and Faith together.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>This is as bad, in making <hi>Christ</hi> but halfe a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. 2. Why do you not to <hi>Christ</hi> and faith, adde prayer and good Workes, <hi>phil.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Iames</hi> 2.24. Thirdly, If Faith be <hi>Christs</hi> partner in accomplishing the worke, it must have part of the glory also.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>That these things follow the ioyning <hi>Christ</hi> and Faith as partners together, I grant; but I suppose that you framed not onely this Answer, but this Obiection also: for you are the first that ever I heard utter such a speech, though it is true, that Iustification is by <hi>Christ,</hi> for he hath purchased it, and true also that we are iustified by Faith, for Faith applyeth it: yet Faith is not <hi>Christs</hi> partner therein; for it is by <hi>Christ</hi> in one respect, and by <hi>Christ</hi> in another, and not by both in one and same respect.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119974:53"/>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>You deny we are iustified by <hi>Christ,</hi> in saying, We were not presented holy before we believe, you contradict <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.28-30. O treason, treason, against <hi>Christ!</hi> Note this.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Christ</hi> doth not in <hi>Iohn</hi> 19. nor in <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. or any where else say, that he presented us holy before we believe, and therefore our saying, we were not, doth not contradict <hi>Christ;</hi> and your saying It doth, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth. Secondly, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.17. saith otherwise as hath been minded, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. And so if gain-saying or pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scripture be Treason, you are guilty, and not we in this thing; and your crying Treason, treason, is but a Scare-crow to frighten People from embracing the truth.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI. Obj. 20. <hi>It is God, and not Faith that justifieth, but he justifieth by Faith, not without it.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Samuel Richardson.</speaker>
                        <p>THrough Faith, that is, through <hi>Christ,</hi> as through his Bloud, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.7. Through redemption in him, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.24. Through him and by him are all one, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. But if you will have it through Faith, it must be so through it as through a pipe; for we do through Faith as through a prospect-glasse see and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our righteousnesse by <hi>Christ,</hi> we receive the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise through Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Yea Brother, we must have it through faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Scripture saith, It is through faith. Secondly, the sense you now minde is the very sense that holds. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119974:53"/>'Tis well you yield to Truth at last; had you done so all this while we should at the farthest distance but have tryed out in what sense we are iustified by <hi>Christ,</hi> and in what sense by faith: but you have till now most stoutly affirmed, that we are not iustified by faith, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Scriptures saith we are; and to make your word good against such Scriptures, you have with all your might laboured to maintain, that by the word <hi>Faith</hi> is meant <hi>Christ:</hi> one Errour it seemes will call in another for assistance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>And this we grant, for we can distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our fight, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.43. and Gods sight, <hi>Job</hi> 9.20. Our sustification in Gods sight was before all time: for, People without sin, without sault before his Throne, <hi>revel.</hi> 15.5. <hi>cant.</hi> 4.7. Whose finnes are laid on <hi>Christ, Isay</hi> 53.11. Against whom is no charge, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.33. Those which are in <hi>Christ,</hi> and reconciled, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 5. Iustified and redeemed, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.7. Whose sinnes are remitted and not imputed to them, must needs be righteous in Gods sight: but the Elect were so when <hi>Christ</hi> dyed; yea, before the World was, but manifest when he appeared, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis good to distinguish betwixt our sight and Gods; we being dim, and he quick-fighted. All things are naked before him, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.13. While we are finners, unbelievers, and uniustified, he seeth us so, and he will see us to be iustified and cleansed when we are so, he seeth us spotty while we are spotty, he doth not see us to be spotlesse till we are spotlesse, he doth not see us through a glasse darkly, much lesse through a false glasse, he seeth us iust as we be; if we see our selves silthy, he seeth it more clearly; if our hearts condemne us, he much more, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. And so to your Reason I reply, that when we are without sin or fault, when God cannot lay ought to our charge, when we are redeemed, our
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119974:54"/>sinnes remitted, not imputed to us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then we shall be righteous in Gods fight, but not before, and this is at <hi>Christs</hi> next appearing, as before proved.</p>
                        <p>If you say, God saw us righteous before the world was; then I say, God also before the world was saw Christ ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing. If you say God saw us iustified from eternity; I say, God also from eternity saw us Believers: so that we are not iustified in Gods sight, till we are Believers in Gods sight; God doth not see us compleat before God seeth <hi>Christs</hi> second comming.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object.</hi> 21. <hi>By Faith, rom.</hi> 4.13. <hi>is not meant Christ, for Scripture never calleth Christ Faith.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>By the word <hi>Faith</hi> there is meant <hi>Christ,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is our righteousnesse. For,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Though <hi>Christ</hi> be our righteousnesse, yet the word <hi>Faith</hi> is not <hi>Christ,</hi> for <hi>Christ</hi> is our righteousnesse through saith: Him we have won, and in him we are found: when we have that righteousnesse, which is through the faith of <hi>Christ, phil.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p n="1">1. Faith and <hi>Christs</hi> righteousnesse are severall things, 2 <hi>peter</hi> 1.1.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Also <hi>Christ</hi> and the Faith of <hi>Christ</hi> by which we are iustified are severall things, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p n="2">2. God hath made <hi>Christ</hi> our righteousnesse, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 1.30. 3. The Title, <hi>The Lord our righteousnesse,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs onely to him, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>This is true, and as true that He is our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, or <hi>The Lord our righteousnesse,</hi> through faith he is not our <hi>propitiation,</hi> much lesse Iustification, otherwise than <hi>Through Faith in his Bloud; thus God sets him forth, rom.</hi> 3.25.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Fourthly, Faith is not our righteousnesse, for Faith shall cease, but our righteousnesse shall be for ever, <hi>Isay</hi> 51.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>You again wrest the <hi>Obiection,</hi> which doth not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119974:54"/>say, Faith is our righteousnesse, but it saith, The Faith specified <hi>rom.</hi> 4.13. is not <hi>Christ.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Secondly, the everlasting righteousnesse which <hi>Christ</hi> purchased is ours by Faith, as before proved.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, you did say, It was conveighed through Faith as through a pipe, or seen through Faith as through a prospect-glasse, and have you already forgot it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Fifthly, <hi>Christs</hi> righteousnesse is as a garment without us, not within us, but Faith is within us, <hi>revel.</hi> 19.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.9-13. <hi>Isay</hi> 61.10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Christ</hi> (which as you say) <hi>is made unto us righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> is not only without and about us, but within us also: <hi>He dwels in our hearts by Faith, Ephes.</hi> 3.17. Also I could tell you that these Scriptures are not yet accomplisht. But of this before.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Sixthly, our righteousnesse is in <hi>Christ,</hi> not in us, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Isay</hi> 45.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>That righteousnesse should be in <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> by faith in us, and yet the said righteousnesse not in us, is more strange than true.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Our righteousnesse was not brought in in <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> time, but at seventy VVeekes end, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. But Faith was brought in before, even in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>That righteousnesse which is through faith must needs be as soon as faith through which it is. I thinke.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, righteousnesse through faith was brought in in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, as it is brought in now; for he is as a paterne held forth to us; that iust as it was with him it shall be with all that become righteous. He believed, and it was counted to him for righteousnesse, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, It was then brought in, in respect of promise; and it is not yet brought in, in full accomplishment, we are not crowned with righteousnesse yet, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Eighthly, the Saints counted <hi>Christ,</hi> and not faith their righteousnesse, <hi>psal.</hi> 71.16-24. <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.29.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:119974:55"/>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>The <hi>Obiection</hi> which you now answer, doth not say, that the Saints account Faith, or account not <hi>Christ</hi> their righteousnesse: also the Saints did by faith receive <hi>Christ</hi> their righteousnesse; as before proved.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Ninthly, <hi>Christ</hi> is all in all, and in all things to have the preheminence, <hi>col.</hi> 1.18. 3.11. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Paul</hi> who reckoned <hi>Christ</hi> all in all, and yielded him the preheminence sought that righteousnesse which is through the Faith of <hi>Christ, phil.</hi> 3.8, 9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>If faith could have been righteousnesse to us, <hi>Christ</hi> might have been spared.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Also, Were <hi>Christ</hi> our righteousnesse without or before believing, faith might be spared: then also un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers would share as deep in <hi>Christ</hi> as believers: but they do not, <hi>phil.</hi> 3.8, 9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Eleventhly, Faith is not this righteousnesse, for this righteousnesse is through faith, <hi>phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>rom.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>Your whole drift in your large Answers to the 18, 20. and this 21. <hi>Obiection</hi> hath been to maintein, that when ever Scripture saith, We are justified through faith: by the word <hi>Faith</hi> is meant <hi>Christ:</hi> for, <hi>'Tis through him:</hi> and now you say, Faith cannot be our righteousnesse, for it is through Faith.</p>
                        <p>If by the word faith here, (as you by your rule teach) is meant <hi>Christ,</hi> then in proper speech it is, that <hi>Christ</hi> cannot be our righteousnesse, because our righteousnesse is through <hi>Christ.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You oft times say, <hi>Christ is righteousnesse:</hi> and oft you say, that <hi>Our righteousnesse is through Christ:</hi> and here you say, that cannot be our righteousnesse through which it is: and how these things will hold together, Iudge Reader. But the Truth is, you would now have the word <hi>Faith</hi> to be meant <hi>Faith</hi> and not <hi>Christ,</hi> as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is, yet this reason with the ten reasons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119974:55"/>it, is brought to prove that by the word <hi>Faith, rom.</hi> 4.13. is meant <hi>Christ;</hi> and to answer that <hi>Obiection</hi> that saith, It is not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Twelftly, the Saints expect not acceptation, for ought in them, or acted by them, but mention <hi>Christs</hi> righteousnesse only, <hi>psal.</hi> 71.10-16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>And <hi>Paul</hi> was in this Saint-like temper, in seeking to be found in <hi>Christ,</hi> that is, not having his own, but that righteousnesse which is through the faith of <hi>Christ, phil.</hi> 3.8, 9. So that we may say, (as Scripture doth) that <hi>Righteousnesse is through Faith in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> and yet not expect acceptation for ought acted by us, but onely make mention of his righteousnesse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Thirteenthly, Faith apart from <hi>Christ</hi> is no righteousnesse at all, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 15.17. Though filled with Christ the powerfullest thing that is, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.16. He is our Bread, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. Our Life, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. Which Life we <hi>now</hi> enioy by faith, which Faith evidenceth things not seen, but some make a god of believing, fetch their comfort from it, and venter their salvation on it, had they lived on, and prised Christ as their believing, I had spared my labour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>But Faith cannot be apart from Christ, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.19, 20. yea, you affirme <hi>p.</hi> 28. that Faith as a relative depends on Christ; so that where one is the other is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so: and that you should see these inseparable, and yet when you please, separate them, is to me strange. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, 'Tis true that Christ is our Bread, and Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But he is thus by Faith; he by believing is received and become ours, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. He that believeth on him, hath him; and he that hath him hath life; he that hath not him hath not life, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.10, 11, 12.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, that our present enjoyments are by faith; and that faith is an evidence of things unseen is the thing I maintain. And had you thus wrote alwayes, I had spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119974:56"/>my labour in opposing you: this being that that I stand for.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, those that make a god of their believing have not (I thinke) the faith of Gods Elect: but we do not in saying (as Scripture saith) that <hi>We are iustified by faith,</hi> make a god of believing.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, your labour herein hath not been to confute such as make a god of believing, or that extoll that above Christ; but to confute such as do say, <hi>We are iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith in Iesus Christ.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Object. 22. <hi>Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteousnesse.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>So <hi>Phinehas</hi> executed Iudgement which was imputed to him for righteousnesse, <hi>Psal.</hi> 106.30. that is, a righteous action.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, If <hi>Abrahams</hi> believing were counted for righteousnesse, then it was his righteousnesse, but Christ onely is so; for nothing makes us righteous but he, <hi>rom.</hi> 5.19. And believing implies righteousnesse in another, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.7. He is our righteousnesse, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6. Peace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14. Propitiation, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25. Redeemer, Saviour, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life; who hath him, hath all; who hath not him, hath nothing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>That faith was reckoned to <hi>Abraham</hi> for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse is Scripture, <hi>romans</hi> 4.9. That then it was his righteousnesse is your consequence.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that faith, and also executing Iudgement are both righteous actions, I grant, and adde another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of yours, that <hi>Faith is a requisite in every good worke, without which it is not well done, nor pleasing to God.</hi> And this also is a Truth, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Abel</hi> offering in faith was accepted, <hi>And he had the witnesse that he was righteous, verse</hi> 4. <hi>Noah</hi> by faith did what he did, <hi>And became heir of the righteous, which is by faith, verse</hi> 5. Thus with <hi>Enoch, Abraham, Jacob, Moses, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rak,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119974:56"/>Gidion, Sampson;</hi> yea all, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. their Actions being not onely things commanded, but also done in faith were righteous Actions, not else; and so <hi>Phinehas</hi> his Action had not been imputed for righteousnesse, had it not been done in faith, and Christ is our Propitiation, no otherwise than through faith, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.25. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves hath Christ, and with him all things; he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not hath nothing, as in your quotation, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10, 11, 12. Christ is indeed our meritorious righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, Is ours by faith? Also, we do not say, Faith, or any thing beside Christ (as God) can make us righteous. But you wrest our words as you do Scripture.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XII. Object. <hi>Justification is after calling,</hi> Rom. 8.30.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Samuel Richardson.</speaker>
                        <p>THen not by faith, for we believe when we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and if we are Believers, and yet not justified; it is because it could not iustifie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>We may be justified by faith, and yet not till after we believe: for faith applyeth things to come, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1, 2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Secondly, though the Elect are justified before they believe, yet they receive it not till then; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it by faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. We receive our priviledges in this order; first calling, then Iustification, and then glorification.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p>That God should worke after one order, and faith receive after another; that God should iustifie first,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119974:57"/>and call afterward; and a grounded faith apply, calling first, and Iustification afterward, is more strange than true.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.30. speakes of Gods orderly work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not of our receiving; the words are, <hi>Moreover whom he predestinated, them he also called, and whom he called, them he also iustified, and whom he iustified, them he</hi> (to wit, God) <hi>also glorified.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thirdly, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. speakes not of that receiving, remission of sinnes that is by faith, but of another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, which followeth believing; <hi>To him give all the Prophets witnesse that through his Name whoever believeth on him shall receive remission of sinnes. Whosoever</hi> for the present <hi>believeth shall receive, &amp;c.</hi> to wit, afterward.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Obiect.</hi> 24. Faith is a condition required to salvation; for, <hi>He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved, he that believes not shall be damned, Marke</hi> 16.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p n="1">1. Faith is no cause or condition of salvation, but this is a rule for Gospel preaching. 2. If faith be a requisite without which we cannot be saved, then is salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Works. 3. Then is the covenant of grace, neither free or absolute; if obiected, God gives what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. I answer, Then is the condition easie to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but a condition it is still; but it is free without condition on our part. For,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kilc.</speaker>
                        <p n="1">1. I will not uphold this <hi>Obiection.</hi> 2. You do wrest the <hi>Obiection,</hi> in adding the word <hi>cause;</hi> for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition required thereto is one thing, and and a cause thereof is another, this being (as you grant a rule for Gospel preaching, Gospel preachers should observe it: but you in saying We may be saved without believing, go against this rule. 4. Though faith be not a conditional cause of, yet it is so requisite to salvation, that whoso be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not (to wit, at all) shall be damned, <hi>Marke</hi> 16. and never see life, but abide under wrath, and die in his
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119974:57"/>sins, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.36. &amp; 8.21-24. 5ly, Gods working in us, what he requireth of us, doth not disanul, but extol his freenes, and tendeth to the comfort &amp; not the discomfort of the Saints, so that they can bodly say, To us Lord thou wilt ordain peace: for thou hast wrought al our works for us, <hi>Isa.</hi> 26.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>First, The Covenant of grace was never made with man, but with Christ onely, <hi>Ps.</hi> 89.19-24-27. Secondly, therefore nothing as a condition, without which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be sav'd, is of the elect required, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. Salvation dependeth not on believing, but on Christ, <hi>John</hi> 14.19. Because I live, ye shall live.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p n="1">1. Without arguments, Scripture may prove the Covenant of grace to be free; But that would be needlesse, being not herein opposed. But your saying, God never made it with man, but only with Christ, is comfortlesse and false; comfortles: for if made only with Christ; it must be performed onely with Christ. False, for first, <hi>Ps.</hi> 89. doth not say, it was not made with man. 2. It was made with <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.1. and with his seed, vers. 7. with the whole house of Israel and house of Iudah, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.32, 33, 34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Eze.</hi> 34.25. but these are men <hi>Eze.</hi> 34.30, 31. and I by faith, depend on Christ for salvation: also these words, because I live, ye shall also. Christ spake to believers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>Thirdly, Faith is a fruit of this Covenant. 4. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect were ever in this Covenant, being ever in Christ, which is this Covenant. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3, 4. <hi>Esay.</hi> 42.6. &amp; 49.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith is no fruit of this Covenant, for it was not made with any till they did believe: when it was made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> he was a believer, and his feed with whom it is made, and shall be establisht, are onely the believing feed, <hi>In Isaac this seed is called, Gen.</hi> 17.19.21.12. that is, The children of the promise, and not the children after the flesh, are counted for the seed. <hi>Ro.</hi> 9.7.8. such as are Christs are <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed, and heirs according to promise, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. &amp; 4.28, 31. And they that are Christs have crucified the flesh with the affections and lusts, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. mark it
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119974:58"/>well. Such as have not (in some measure) crucified the flesh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not Christs, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24. and they that are not Christs, are not <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed according to promise, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. but God doth make, and will establish his Covenant with that seed only, which is according to promise, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.19.21.12. 25th <hi>Object.</hi> To be justified, is to be pronounced just.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>To be justified, is to be made just.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>To be justified, is to be made just: it hath more in it then a bare pronuntiation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>Men are made just, when the habit of justice is put into them: so God made man. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>And when this habit of justice (being now lost) is by Christ to us restored, we shall be justified or made just.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p n="2">2. Men are made just, by the justice of another. Christs satisfaction, is our justification. As by one mans disobedience many were made sinners: so by the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of one, many are made righteous, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>First, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. is by you abused, which saith, So by the obedience of one, many shall be made righteous. But you write many are. Secondly, you also confound your selfe, in saying, His satisfaction is our juctification, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so saying, We are justified by his justice, as if not only his obedient suffering, but also his holy walking, were impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, which cannot stand with Gods justice, as before declared. Thirdly, His satisfaction procureth, but is not our justification: his bearing iniquity is the cause, justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation the effect. <hi>Esay.</hi> 53.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>We are made just by sentence: so men justify them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, <hi>Job</hi> 9.20. or the wicked, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15. This is oft times worth nothing, being but a shadow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>Therefore, though you and a thousand more tell me, that your justification is already effected, I seeing remnants of injustice in you, believe you not; knowing such words to be but winde: God will not say it, till it be so: He will nor clear the guilty, <hi>Ex.</hi> 34.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>But declaring one just, maketh him not so: for first,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119974:58"/>then he was not so before. 2. Then we make God so (which is blasphemy) 3. Then tis good to justify the wicked.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>These ill consequences fall on their heads that doe say, Declaring a man iust doth make him so, not on others.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p n="4">4. God by his Spirit, declares to our souls, that we are iust, which if we were not when he was on the crosse, then he iustifieth the wicked: they being iust or wicked; if iust, then, his declaring them to be so, makes them not so: if not iust, then wicked; and he will not clear the guilty. <hi>Ex.</hi> 34.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>That God clears not the guilty is true, and as true, that you and I are as yet in some things guilty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though I dare not think you destitute of Gods Spirit, yet sure I am, that Gods Spirit doth not declare unto your soul, that you are in accompishment instified already, but are in respect of purpose, prophesie, promise, purchase, and faith (that is) God hath purposed, and promised it, Christ hath purchased it, and Faith applieth it. Believers were iustified in respect of purpose, before the world was, in respect of prophesie and promise before Christ dyed: In respect of purchase when he dyed; and by faiths applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when they believe, and shall be iustified effectually in accomplishment, in performance, and in respect of actuall enioyment, when Christ again appeareth, but not before, as hath been proved: he came to purchase, and will come to effect.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p n="5">5. Men are not iustified, because declared so to be, but declared to be so, because they are so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>Therefore, God will not declare us iust till we are: and your saying you are iust, before you are, is untrue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>In iustification are three essentials: sinners to be made iust, God to make iust, and the means by which, is Christs blood, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Isaiah</hi> said, He should iustifie many, 45.25. which he fulfilled, when he was made sinne, <hi>Is.</hi> 53.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. iustification is where satisfaction is, as all in <hi>Adam</hi> by his disobedience were made sinners: so
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119974:59"/>all in Christ by his obedience were made righteous <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>These requisites in iustification, to wit, sinners to be made, God to make iust, and Christs bloud as a means to procure it, I own: but that he when he dyed, effected what he dyed for, I deny: but the effect followeth the cause. He hath been, that we might be, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>Iustification, is first to be considered in purpose: Thus the Elect were saved ere the world was, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10. which is called Iustification, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.7. to wit, in respect of purpose.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>That it is already in purpose and purchase to, I main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: and that it is effected or accomplisht, is that which I deny.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p n="2">2. It is to be considered in the effecting and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of it, by the means Iesus Christ, who did justifie many, <hi>Is.</hi> 53. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. it is actually done, as the Priests bore Israelites names, <hi>Ex.</hi> 28.21. So Christ bore their names and persons, who should be iustified and saved, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>I have declared that Christ hath but purchased, and not effected iustification, as yet, though he shall. And your quotations, <hi>Is.</hi> 53. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. say, he shall, and doe not say (as you doe) that he did justifie, and as <hi>Aaron</hi> the Type, so Christ the antitype, doth by interceding bear the names of such as shall be iustified and saved: <hi>Ergo.</hi> They are not iustified and saved as yet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>Christ tooke not onely the nature, but also the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sous of the elect: else he answereth not the types, else he did as much for all, as any; yea, else he bore not the sins of any.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>Your disjoyning a mans nature from his person, is as frivolous as your former setting faith a part from Christ, and the act of faith from the nature of it, and therefore not worth the answering.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>Iustification being accomplisht, it is Christs plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119974:59"/>to reveale it, to those to whom it belongeth, by his Spirit, Word and Ordinances, that they might enjoy the comfort of it: the effect of which declaration, begetteth in them love to God, and carrieth the soul out of it self to Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>The discoveries of love, doth indeed produce such effects; but to say the effect of such declarations, begets love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is non-sense: for our love to God, is the effect of his declarration of love to us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17. Secondly, God discovers Iustification to those to whom it belongeth before it be accomplisht: therefore its so often said, We are instified by faith. Yea, your point proves this, for the accomplishment heerof was, say you, when Christ dyed: but it was discovered, to <hi>Abraham</hi> and other believers before Christ dyed.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, When iustification is accomplisht, we shall have such union with God, and knowledge of God, that we shall not need word or ordinances to discover it to us; neither want the comfort of it, when (in accomplishment) all the seed of <hi>Israel</hi> shall be iustified, they shall glory, <hi>Is.</hi> 45.25.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>The efficient cause of iustification, or salvation, is Gods love: the materiall cause, Christs death: the end or finall cause, Gods glory.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>These causes I deny not: but adde this, That the meritorious cause goes before the effect: but of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>The work being done, the Spirit reveals, faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, and good workes declare that it is done for us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>The Spirit reveals, and faith receives things as they be, or as the word holdeth them forth: Namely, first, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, afterwardin performance: first, purchased, afterward ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; the spirit revealeth, and faith receiveth Christ come, a high Priest of good things to come, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.11. Now to your quotations. The Spirit revealing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. hath
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119974:60"/>not reference to the time past nor present, but to the glory that shall be shewed to us, as verse 17, 18. and <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. speaks of that receiving remission of sins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is after sanctification, by faith in Christ.</p>
                        <p>26. <hi>Object.</hi> Iustification is onely in the conscience, and men are not iustified till sin be taken out of their conscience.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>Iustification is in Christ. See <hi>Epistle.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>First, I own the later part, but not the first part of this obiection: Secondly, Iustification is in Christ, and by him purchased; also it is in the conscience, by faith applyed: See my answer to your <hi>Epistle.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p>Secondly, Then faith doth not iustifie, for it takes not sin out of the conscience.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p n="1">1. This Obiection doth not say, faith iustifieth, or takes sin out of the conscience: but secondly,, God by giving faith doth (by degrees) take sin out of the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.14. And he that begins this good work, wil perfect it til the day of Christ: <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.18.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p n="3">3. Men may believe, and not see sin taken out of their consciences, <hi>Is.</hi> 50.10, 11 to see all sin taken out of the conscience, is a great light.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>The light is as great, to see our selves iustified, as to see all sin taken out of our consciences: for (as you have said) to be iustified, is to be made iust; and made iust, we are not, till our injustice be done away: neither is that done away, while it abideth in the conscience. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so I have not yet forgotten your once minding this to be the summe of all; That while Christ was one the crosse, he tooke away, and utterly destroyed all his peoples sinnes, for ever: If all their fins were then destroyed, not in part onely, but utterly (not for a little while, but) for ever: how can they now have being in the conscience, if took away, then and that for ever, how can they still remain?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p n="4">4. If the knowing I believe, takes away my sinne, faith doth not; for to believe is one thing &amp; to know it is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119974:60"/>another; and so, neither God, nor his Spirit, nor Christ, nor faith, a part or together, takes them away: but the knowing we believe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p>To say faith, or the knowing we believe, takes fin out of the conscience, are your expressions not ours: but we doe and will say, <hi>That God purifies our hearts by faith, Acts</hi> 15.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>R.</speaker>
                        <p n="5">5. If assurance of justification, be justification, then are some believers unjustified, which have sin in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, and are deserted, and enjoy not assurance, <hi>Ps.</hi> 88. Sixtly, If justification consisteth in taking fin out of the conscience, then every act of sin maketh us unjustified, till we act faith to take it out of the conscience, and then we appear to God justified, and unjustified in ten minutes: and then we have not faith, till we have assurance, or till fin be taken out of our conscience; and so such children of God as walke in darknesse, are concluded to be in their finues.</p>
                        <p>Iustification dependeth not on our believing it; but he that saveth us, justifieth us; even <hi>Christ</hi> onely; who is our justification, salvation, and all in all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>K.</speaker>
                        <p n="1">1. We do not say assurance of justification, is justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Secondly, Every act of sin is injustice: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are not justified, or made just, while acts of sin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main. Thirdly, That we appear to God iustified now, and then uniustified again, will not follow: but being already iustified in respect of purpose, prophesie, promise and purchase (as was shewen) we thus appear to God now, and shall doe till we are iustified in accomplishment and per formance: the crown of righteousnesse is now safely laid up for us; and shall at that day be given to us: as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Though we are not iustified till iniustice be taken out of our consciences, yet faith is before that time. First God by (giving) faith purifies, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. Secondly, faith pitcheth on things to come; it evidenceth things not seen <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1.</p>
                        <pb n="108" facs="tcp:119974:61"/>
                        <p> Fiftly, Though iustification and salvation, depend not on believing, yet it followeth believing: and though Christ iustifieth and saveth, and is all in all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, and saveth believers onely, and is all in all onely to them, as proved from <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.4.9.10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>Errata</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reade page</hi> 5 <hi>line</hi> 10 <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. <hi>for</hi> 19. <hi>reade</hi> 39. <hi>p.</hi> 7 <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> 32. <hi>p.</hi> 9 <hi>l.</hi> 12, <hi>&amp;</hi> 30 <hi>&amp;</hi> 32 <hi>for ver. r.</hi> Rev. <hi>p.</hi> 20 <hi>l</hi> 29 <hi>f. children of r.</hi> children of Israel. <hi>p.</hi> 24 <hi>l.</hi> 21 <hi>f. Eph.</hi> 1.14. <hi>r.</hi> Hebr. 9.11. <hi>p.</hi> 29 <hi>f. particle r.</hi> particular. <hi>p.</hi> 32 <hi>l.</hi> 21 <hi>for Iohn</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> Job 13. <hi>p.</hi> 42 <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>f. Rom.</hi> 3.14. <hi>r.</hi> Acts 3.19. <hi>p.</hi> 43 <hi>l.</hi> 16 <hi>for</hi> 48. <hi>r.</hi> 40. <hi>p.</hi> 55 <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>for before, r.</hi> be before. <hi>l.</hi> 34. <hi>r.</hi> Kilcop. <hi>p.</hi> 73 <hi>l.</hi> 28 <hi>for in r.</hi> ou. <hi>p,</hi> 58. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>for</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 30. <hi>for no r,</hi> not. <hi>p.</hi> 80 <hi>l.</hi> 20 <hi>for faith of, reade</hi> faith in. <hi>p.</hi> 91. <hi>l.</hi> 35. <hi>for Christ, r.</hi> faith. <hi>p.</hi> 98 <hi>l.</hi> 34. <hi>for righteous, r.</hi> righteousnesse. <hi>What other faults thou findest which have escaped me, in love passe over.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Postscript.</hi> I commend to thy further view the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Robert Maton.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>